<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Jacinta&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-512.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A toolbox for trait-based forecasting</title>
      <link>/project/toolbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/toolbox/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#tools-for-forcasting-or-predicting&#34;&gt;Tools for forcasting or predicting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#resources-for-forcasting&#34;&gt;Resources for forcasting&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#macroclimate&#34;&gt;Macroclimate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#microclimate&#34;&gt;Microclimate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#microclimate-simulation-packages-for-r&#34;&gt;Microclimate simulation packages for &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#things-to-consider&#34;&gt;Things to consider&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#traits&#34;&gt;Traits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#r-packages-for-modelling&#34;&gt;R packages for modelling&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#nichemapr-deb-biophysical-ecology&#34;&gt;NicheMapR, DEB &amp;amp; biophysical ecology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#international-symposium-and-thematic-school-on-deb-theory-for-metabolic-organisation&#34;&gt;International Symposium and Thematic School on DEB Theory for Metabolic Organisation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;tools-for-forcasting-or-predicting&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Tools for forcasting or predicting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am interested in developing a toolbox for biologists to make trait-based predictions or forecasts about how ectotherms respond to environmental change that are grounded in theory. Fostering stronger links between our understanding of terrestrial ectotherm thermal biology and the aquatic realm is important to identify general patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;resources-for-forcasting&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Resources for forcasting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good model needs good input data!&lt;br /&gt;
A pretty important component of modelling species responses to environmental variables are the environmental variables themselves. In fact, it’s already half the data. Ideally, you would have climatic data at the scale of the target organism, which I will generally refer to as &lt;strong&gt;microclimate&lt;/strong&gt;, but this is often a challenge to acquire. But if you have access to climate data, e.g. gridded weather stations which I will refer to as &lt;strong&gt;macroclimate&lt;/strong&gt;, then there are some solutions for generating microclimate data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most experimental biologists will have access to plenty of data on organism traits but may not have the right environmental data for a model. The good news is with the increasing ease of generating and storing big data, data is now more accessible than ever before!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;macroclimate&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Macroclimate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have access to gridded weather station data for your area of interest, there are some publicly available datasets online for various environmental variables at various scales and resolutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldclim.org/&#34;&gt;WorldClim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.climond.org/&#34;&gt;CliMond&lt;/a&gt; with CLIMEX and Bioclim datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cru.uea.ac.uk/&#34;&gt;Climatic Research Unit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;microclimate&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Microclimate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are currently a few publicly available datasets of pre-calculated microclimate grids. All these examples were made using &lt;code&gt;NicheMapR&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/sdata20146&#34;&gt;microlim&lt;/a&gt; for global scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://knb.ecoinformatics.org/knb/d1/mn/v2/object/knb.92484.39&#34;&gt;MicroclimOz&lt;/a&gt; for Australia only (the lucky country)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://knb.ecoinformatics.org/view/urn:uuid:b8a6dbfd-3a97-4a24-91d5-1648fdba1648&#34;&gt;MicroclimUS&lt;/a&gt; for USA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;microclimate-simulation-packages-for-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Microclimate simulation packages for &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few packages for &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; to simulate microclimates from gridded macroclimate data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mrke.github.io&#34;&gt;NicheMapR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.13093&#34;&gt;Microclima&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://trenchproject.github.io/tools/TrenchR/&#34;&gt;TrenchR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one I used in my work is &lt;code&gt;NicheMapR&lt;/code&gt;. The default function to generate microclimate in &lt;code&gt;NicheMapR&lt;/code&gt; uses the Climatic Research Unit dataset to generate default microclimate output. I used input data at a higher spatial and temporal resolution than the default setting, in addition to querying gridded soil type data. Although the input data to run my scripts is not available, &lt;code&gt;NicheMapR&lt;/code&gt; was used to generate the microclim and MicroclimOz datasets which are publicly available under certain soil type parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;things-to-consider&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Things to consider&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check if the environmental datasets are at the resolution and scale appropriate for your intended purposes. If you want to simulate microclimate, you need to make sure you have all the environmental variables needed for the microclimate package: temperature, precipitation, soil type, topography, wind speed, solar radiation etc. You may have to collate input data from multiple sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;traits&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Traits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are even a few databases for organism trait data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Insect Developmental Database (&lt;a href=&#34;https://nucleus.iaea.org/sites/naipc/twd/Lists/News/DispForm.aspx?ID=291&amp;amp;ContentTypeId=0x0100E051773707C04949A2F50750BBDBE134&#34;&gt;IDD&lt;/a&gt;) contains temperature-rate data for mostly insect species of agricultural interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For physiological limits &lt;a href=&#34;https://datadryad.org/resource/doi:10.5061/dryad.1cv08/7&#34;&gt;GlobTherm&lt;/a&gt; is a great initiative but covers CtMax and CtMin only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few recent metaanalyses have combed through the thermal biology literature so you don’t have to! Then you can extract the information you want. Isn’t open, reproducible science great? Here’s a recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://datadryad.org/resource/doi:10.5061/dryad.56s5d84&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dell et al. 2013 complied a &lt;a href=&#34;https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1890/12-2060.1&#34;&gt;dataset&lt;/a&gt; on various biological/ecological traits measured at different tempertures for species from all habitats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;r-packages-for-modelling&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;R packages for modelling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my PhD I wrote a custom function for my code to calculate development rate. But there is also a package for that!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/devRate/index.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;devRate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a package with commonly used temperature-rate functions, from statistical functions to biophysical ones. You can get it from CRAN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a similar package called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/padpadpadpad/rTPC&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rTPC&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not on CRAN but is available on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;nichemapr-deb-biophysical-ecology&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NicheMapR, DEB &amp;amp; biophysical ecology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the NicheMapR package is a pretty complete toolkit to model the biology of an organism based on its environment and available resources. Not only does it have a microclimate model but it also has an implementation of the standard DEB model and a biophysical heat and water budget model for ecotherms and endotherms. All that is missing are the correct input parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heat and/or water budget equations are useful for calculating the body temperature of an organism but don’t measure growth or development. You could use the estimates of body temperture for calculating development/growth rates but for most small ectotherms that are isothermic, this seems a bit excessive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;deb-parameters-and-add-my-pet&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;DEB parameters and Add-My-Pet&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find standard DEB parameters at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bio.vu.nl/thb/deb/deblab/add_my_pet/&#34;&gt;Add-My-Pet&lt;/a&gt; and there is a vignette in NicheMapR which goes through the ectotherm model, the DEB model and how to use the DEB parameters from Add-My-Pet in NicheMapR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;international-symposium-and-thematic-school-on-deb-theory-for-metabolic-organisation&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;International Symposium and Thematic School on DEB Theory for Metabolic Organisation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested in learning Dynamic Energy Budget modelling? There is an international symposium, tele-course and school/workshop that is an intensive course in DEB and its applications. The symposium is held every two years. The most recent one was &lt;a href=&#34;https://deb2019.sciencesconf.org/&#34;&gt;April 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the resources available you can pretty much develop a mechanistic model without collecting your own data.&lt;br /&gt;
If there are other useful datasets or links not listed here, let me know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biostatistics tutorials</title>
      <link>/project/biostats-tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/biostats-tutorials/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;biostats.tutorials&lt;/code&gt; is an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; package of &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorials for introductory biostatistics and &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;set-up&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Set up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to set up our computer to start using tutorials in R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow this checklist in order to make sure you are set up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed R version 4.0 or above? - if not, install/update R
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can check your R package version using &lt;code&gt;R.version()$version.string&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed RStudio version 1.0.136 or above? - if not install/update RStudio
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can check your RStudio version using &lt;code&gt;RStudio.Version()$version&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed the following packages? - if not use &lt;code&gt;install.packages()&lt;/code&gt; to do so
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; - needed to run the tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;remotes&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;devtools&lt;/code&gt;) - needed to install the tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; - for displaying content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If everything works then you should see a Tutorials tab in one of your RStudio windows (perhaps next to Environment and History)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;installing-the-tutorials&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installing the tutorials&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we need to install the tutorial. The tutorials are stored in a Package available on GitHub. You will only have to install the package once at the beginning.&lt;br /&gt;
Use the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;jacintak/biostats&amp;quot;, dependencies = TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are asked to install any other packages, choose yes but don’t do any compiling (press no if asked).&lt;br /&gt;
If the package installed properly, you should automatically see the tutorials in the Tutorial tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;running-a-tutorial&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Running a tutorial&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be able to run a tutorial from the Tutorial tab when you open RStudio without needing to do anything.&lt;br /&gt;
Make sure it’s a tutorial from the &lt;code&gt;biostats.tutorials&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you click run tutorial, the tutorial will show up in the tab. You can click the “Show in new window” icon to open it in another window. Press the “Home” icon to return to the Tutorials tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn’t work use this code and the tutorial will open in another window:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;learnr::run_tutorial(&amp;quot;&amp;lt;insert name of the tutorial to run&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, package = &amp;quot;biostats.tutorials&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If neither works, check that the &lt;code&gt;biostats.tutorials&lt;/code&gt; package installed properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quit a tutorial by pressing the “Stop” icon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>colRoz</title>
      <link>/project/colRoz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/colRoz/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link href=&#34;index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; /&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;ColRoz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting ectotherm life cycles</title>
      <link>/project/life-cycles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/life-cycles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Move. Adapt. Die. Ectotherms have adapted their entire life cycle to the rhythm of the seasons. The egg stage is a critical part of insect life cycles that must resist or tolerate environmental fluctuations. How immobile eggs do so and how these mechanisms change in their function or importance over geographical gradients is a complex story.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thermal dependence of biological rates</title>
      <link>/project/temperature-dependence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/temperature-dependence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Temperature affects biological processes on many levels of biological organisation. I am determining how the relationship between rates and temperatures affects processes beyond the individual and on macro scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an SFI funded position with Nicholas Payne&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
