<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>code | Jacinta&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>https://jacintak.github.io/tags/code/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jacintak.github.io/tags/code/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>code</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jacintak.github.io/img/icon-512.png</url>
      <title>code</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/tags/code/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond the valley of intermediate competence</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/purrr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/purrr/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/purrr/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I &lt;a href=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/using-mapply/&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about learning to forego for loops for &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; functions in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;. I’m continuing this journey to replace for loops with &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt;. I’ll be honest and say that my main motivation for learning &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; is the package name 🐱. &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; is a package that does the same things as &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt;; to apply a function over listed data and also has useful functions for manipulating lists and functional programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Objectively, the functionality of &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; is not that different to base functions. There’s an understandable learning curve and resulting benefit when going from for loops to &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; functions, but there’s diminishing return on going from &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; unless you fully leverage the shortcuts of &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; syntax (which I have not). The main advantage of &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; is that it uses the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; syntax and pipes. Overall, I don’t think there’s a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; benefit for using &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; over base, unlike for example the advantages of using &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; over base for graphing, but if your code is already written in &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; then it makes sense to stick to it and have clear and consistent code (if you are used to reading &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; syntax).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you really want to stay on the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; train you can skip learning &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; and jump straight to &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; but I’m a fan of using as fewer dependencies as possible and knowing the base &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; way. There are lots of detailed tutorials about &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; and it’s functions, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://jennybc.github.io/purrr-tutorial/bk01_base-functions.html&#34;&gt;this one that discusses the differences with base functions&lt;/a&gt; so I recommend checking those out. If you’re already familiar with the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; syntax then &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; is no different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some things I’ve learnt about &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; for applying functions to listed data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;lapply&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; takes one argument (data) and applies a function to it. As I found earlier, it’s quite a simple case and doesn’t suit more complex datasets I usually work with. The &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; equivalent is &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the advantages of &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; is that it you can specify the format of the output. That is, &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; takes a list and produces a list, but &lt;code&gt;map_*&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; are a range of output types will give that output type. For example, &lt;code&gt;map_chr&lt;/code&gt; will take a list and produce a character vector. This is handy because it skips an intermediate step to transform your resulting list into your desired output format, such as using &lt;code&gt;do.call&lt;/code&gt; to turn a list into a data frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;an-example&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s use the same code as the previous post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# some data to use as a list
loop_data &amp;lt;- data.frame(col1 = c(11:15), col2 = c(20:24))

# define variable to change
a &amp;lt;- seq(0.2, 1, 0.2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As before, &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; is a data frame with two numeric columns (&lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;code&gt;col2&lt;/code&gt;). We technically won’t use &lt;code&gt;loop_data$col2&lt;/code&gt; but it’s there to create a 5x2 data frame. &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; is a variable that we need for our function with 5 values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to add each element of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;loop_data$col1&lt;/code&gt; and save that in a new column &lt;code&gt;loop_data$col1a&lt;/code&gt;. We will also add &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a column in &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; just so we can keep track of which value was used to calculate &lt;code&gt;col1a&lt;/code&gt;. So the final output should have 25 rows (5 observations in &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; x 5 values of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;) and 4 columns (&lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;col2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;col1a&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s use &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; to do the same thing we did with &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; but using &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; and pipes 🛁&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;loop_data %&amp;gt;% 
  expand_grid(., a) %&amp;gt;% # expand to include all crossed combinations
  group_split(a) %&amp;gt;% # split into lists by the value of a for nested lists
  map_dfr(., function(x){
    x$col1a &amp;lt;- x$col1 + x$a
    return(x)
    }) %&amp;gt;% # apply the function to the list and return a data frame
  summary(.) # show the summary&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##       col1         col2          a           col1a     
##  Min.   :11   Min.   :20   Min.   :0.2   Min.   :11.2  
##  1st Qu.:12   1st Qu.:21   1st Qu.:0.4   1st Qu.:12.4  
##  Median :13   Median :22   Median :0.6   Median :13.6  
##  Mean   :13   Mean   :22   Mean   :0.6   Mean   :13.6  
##  3rd Qu.:14   3rd Qu.:23   3rd Qu.:0.8   3rd Qu.:14.8  
##  Max.   :15   Max.   :24   Max.   :1.0   Max.   :16.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with piping this is what’s happening:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first line is specifying our list &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; to be sent down the pipe (&lt;code&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/code&gt;). Pipes are read sequentially and the output of one line is used as the input of the next line. This intermediate object is indicated by the dot (&lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;). Sometimes the dot can be left out if the arguments are presented to the function in the expected order but I find it useful to type everything out when learning anyway so that it’s clear what the arguments are. The dot is particularly needed when using base functions within a pipe, as seen in the last line with &lt;code&gt;summary(.)&lt;/code&gt; because these functions are expecting an argument that &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; functions know how to deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I use &lt;code&gt;tidyr::expand_grid&lt;/code&gt; to create a data frame of all combinations of &lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;. This has a benefit of adding &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a column.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I use &lt;code&gt;group_split&lt;/code&gt; to group the crossed data frame based on values of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;. This produces a tibble which are essentially &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; lists. &lt;code&gt;split&lt;/code&gt; is a base equivalent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then I apply the actual function over the list and specify that I want the output to be a single data frame (the &lt;code&gt;_dfr&lt;/code&gt; suffix). This is the equivalent of doing &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;do.call&lt;/code&gt; in the same function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally I use the base &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; function &lt;code&gt;summary&lt;/code&gt; to show the summary statistics of the result to check it works. There isn’t a &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; equivalent of &lt;code&gt;summary&lt;/code&gt; so we must use the dot within the function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result is exactly the same as the original &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; code. Here is the &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; function from the previous post to compare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Prepare the answer list
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- replicate(length(a), loop_data, simplify = FALSE)

# add a column using mapply
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- mapply(FUN = cbind, lapply_ans, &amp;quot;a&amp;quot; = a, SIMPLIFY = FALSE)

# apply function
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- lapply(lapply_ans, FUN = lapply_function)

# merge to single data frame
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- do.call(rbind, lapply_ans)

# view the data
summary(lapply_ans)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Side note:
&lt;code&gt;rerun(length(a), loop_data)&lt;/code&gt; behaves exactly the same as &lt;code&gt;replicate(length(a), loop_data, simplify = FALSE)&lt;/code&gt; and is the &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; equivalent (unclear for how long according to the dev notes). Then you’ll need to add &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a column, matching the order of the tibble and set the column names, e.g. &lt;code&gt;rerun(length(a), loop_data) %&amp;gt;% map2(a, bind_cols) %&amp;gt;% map(a=...3, rename)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The differences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’ve taken a slightly different approach. I define all possible combinations I want to use in the calculations then creating grouped lists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I specified the function within the pipe rather than named in the global environment like in the original post. It’s better to name the function if you’re using it multiple times but in this post I’m only using it once, so I’ll get away with it.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; also allows formulas which for simple functions (like adding a constant to all values) will simplify the code and let
you use anonymous functions. I’m not used to the formula method of writing functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of 5 separate lines of code with the base version, in &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; we can do it in a pipe with 4 steps. But you notice that it’s not a huge difference between what the two approaches are doing. Still better than a for loop.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We skipped &lt;code&gt;do.call&lt;/code&gt; by using &lt;code&gt;map_dfr&lt;/code&gt; directly to return a data frame. I could also use &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; and transform the list into a
data frame separately.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;and-another-thing&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;And another thing…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to prepare the input data so that it is crossed; which mean replicating our list across all combinations of &lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;expand_grid&lt;/code&gt; or similar as used above could be helpful for this, and the data frame could be split into nested lists for applying the function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To contrast, this will only add matching rows of &lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; together rather than all combinations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;list(loop_data$col1, a) %&amp;gt;%
  pmap_dfr(function(x, a) {
  df &amp;lt;- data.frame(col1 = x,
                   a = a,
                   col1a = x + a) # add answer to a new column
  return(df)
})&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   col1   a col1a
## 1   11 0.2  11.2
## 2   12 0.4  12.4
## 3   13 0.6  13.6
## 4   14 0.8  14.8
## 5   15 1.0  16.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; is the equivalent of &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt;, then it also doesn’t take multiple inputs, which is why we added &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a column to &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt;. So we turn to &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; and its &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mapply&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt; equivalent of &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt;. Specifically, &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt; allows for any number of arguments for the function. There is another function, &lt;code&gt;map2&lt;/code&gt; that accepts exactly two arguments but &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt; is generalised to allow for more than two. As with &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt;, there are variants with suffixes that specify what output format you want, such as a data frame (&lt;code&gt;pmap_dfr&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; website goes into the syntax differences between &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt; in more &lt;a href=&#34;https://design.tidyverse.org/cs-mapply-pmap.html&#34;&gt;detail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s jump to the example using the same &lt;code&gt;loop_function&lt;/code&gt; as the original post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;pmap&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# A function to add a value a to a data frame x
loop_function &amp;lt;- function(x, a) {
  x$col1a &amp;lt;- x$col1 + a # add answer to a new column
  x$a &amp;lt;-  a
  return(x)
}

loop_data %&amp;gt;% 
  rerun(length(a), .) %&amp;gt;% # replicate the list to populate
  list(a) %&amp;gt;% # define all variables for loop_function within a list
  pmap_dfr(loop_function) %&amp;gt;% # apply the function to the list and return a data frame
  map_dfc(summary) # show the summary&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## # A tibble: 6 x 4
##   col1    col2    col1a   a      
##   &amp;lt;table&amp;gt; &amp;lt;table&amp;gt; &amp;lt;table&amp;gt; &amp;lt;table&amp;gt;
## 1 11      20      11.2    0.2    
## 2 12      21      12.4    0.4    
## 3 13      22      13.6    0.6    
## 4 13      22      13.6    0.6    
## 5 14      23      14.8    0.8    
## 6 15      24      16.0    1.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we don’t have to add &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a column to &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt;, we can specify &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; for the function. &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt; takes a list of arguments for the function, hence we need a list containing both &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;. Don’t make &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; list before adding it to the list of function arguments (i.e. double list) because it won’t match the nth &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; variable with the nth element in the loop_data list, and match by rows within lists. For variety, I’ve used &lt;code&gt;map_dfc&lt;/code&gt; to call the function &lt;code&gt;summary&lt;/code&gt; on the data, rather than &lt;code&gt;summary(.)&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;map_dfc&lt;/code&gt; will apply the function by columns instead of rows and produce a data frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;map2&lt;/code&gt; equivalent is more concise than &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt; for this simple example!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;loop_data %&amp;gt;% 
  rerun(length(a), .) %&amp;gt;% 
  map2_dfr(a, loop_function)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the original &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; example to compare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Prepare the answer list
mapply_ans &amp;lt;- replicate(length(a), loop_data, simplify = FALSE)
# mapply function
mapply_ans &amp;lt;- mapply(mapply_ans, FUN = loop_function, a = a, SIMPLIFY = FALSE)
# merge to single data frame
mapply_ans &amp;lt;- do.call(rbind, mapply_ans)
# view the data
summary(mapply_ans)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could also define &lt;code&gt;loop_function&lt;/code&gt; as an anonymous function within &lt;code&gt;pmap&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure the variables are used in the correct order. e.g. &lt;code&gt;loop_data %&amp;gt;% rerun(length(a), .) %&amp;gt;% map_dfr(loop_function, a)&lt;/code&gt; will run because you are passing &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a variable into &lt;code&gt;loop_function&lt;/code&gt;, but it’s adding &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; by row within individual data frame rather than matching the nth element of the list. So it’s effectively replicating the data frame 5 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it. There are many ways of doing the same thing with simple examples. Hope it helps you create &lt;code&gt;purrr&lt;/code&gt;fectly sensible code to replace for loops and apply functions to lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setup R</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/teaching/introR/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/teaching/introR/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/teaching/introR/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#welcome-to-statistics-and-computation-for-biologists&#34;&gt;Welcome to Statistics and Computation for Biologists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-programming-and-computing&#34;&gt;Why programming and computing?&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#basic-computing-terms&#34;&gt;Basic computing terms&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#drives-folders-files&#34;&gt;Drives, Folders &amp;amp; Files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#directories&#34;&gt;Directories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-r&#34;&gt;Why R?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#why-rstudio&#34;&gt;Why RStudio?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installing-r-and-rstudio&#34;&gt;Installing R and RStudio&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#windows&#34;&gt;Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#mac&#34;&gt;Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#linux&#34;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#chromebook&#34;&gt;Chromebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#opening-r-and-rstudio-for-the-first-time&#34;&gt;Opening R and RStudio for the first time&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#updating-r-and-packages&#34;&gt;Updating R and packages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#creating-a-script&#34;&gt;Creating a script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#setting-up-packages&#34;&gt;Setting up packages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#working-directories&#34;&gt;Working directories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#changing-working-directories&#34;&gt;Changing working directories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#loading-data&#34;&gt;Loading data&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#txt&#34;&gt;.txt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#csv&#34;&gt;.csv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#copying-data&#34;&gt;Copying data&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#try-it-yourself&#34;&gt;Try it yourself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#checking-the-data&#34;&gt;Checking the data&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#data-structure&#34;&gt;Data structure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#summarising-data&#34;&gt;Summarising data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#tips&#34;&gt;Tips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#finding-help&#34;&gt;Finding help&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#final-checklist&#34;&gt;Final checklist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;welcome-to-statistics-and-computation-for-biologists&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Welcome to Statistics and Computation for Biologists&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training to become a scientist can be broken down into two parts. First, there is content to learn - these are technical details or “how to” which come from textbooks, lectures or resources on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, is learning how to define problems and how to solve them. You will see this in action throughout your degree. For example, is your R code not working? Work out why, what’s wrong and what to change to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this module we aim to give you the tools and knowledge to solve your own data science problems. These skills will be important in your later studies or even your career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the following checklist to make sure you are prepared for this semester:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know how to navigate computer directories and addresses to find files or folders?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have R and RStudio installed on your computer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is R up to date? (version 4.0 or above)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know how to set up scripts and directories in RStudio?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know how to import and export data into R in various formats?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve answered no to any of the above questions, then continue on. Some of you may already have R and RStudio installed from previous modules - that’s great! Check that your version and packages are all up to date (Under the Packages tab, click Update). Even so, you can work through this document if you want to check everything works or you need a refresher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-programming-and-computing&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Why programming and computing?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We care about teaching you programming and computing skills because they are important skills in the current workforce and are not to be taken for granted. Programming is not just code, it’s a way of thinking and requires problem solving skills that are applicable to other scenarios. You can apply these skills to a range of problems or examples beyond what we will cover in this module. We will be using R which is classified as a high-level programming language - it’s not the same thing as learning how to use Excel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning programming is like learning a language - there is grammar and syntax and it takes time and effort to learn and to practice. Don’t expect to pick it up like memorising content from a lecture - take it in small steps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;basic-computing-terms&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Basic computing terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t always formally learn computing terminology even if we’ve always been using computers. Here are some general computing concepts we will be using and that we expect you to be familiar with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;drives-folders-files&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Drives, Folders &amp;amp; Files&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In computer science, most commercial operating software are organised in to &lt;strong&gt;drives&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;directories&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;folders&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;strong&gt;files&lt;/strong&gt;. Using Windows as example:
C:/ is a drive (a hard drive). Within the drive, information is sorted in folders (e.g. Documents). Within folders are groups of files which contain information (e.g. my_document.doc). Here, “.doc” is the file extension that tells the computer what kind of file it is and what program to use to read the information (a Word document). Folders within folders are sometimes called sub-folders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commercial computers tend to have only one drive but you can have as many folders and files as you want. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;C: (the hard drive)
  -&amp;gt; my documents (within drive C)
      -&amp;gt; file A (within my documents)
      -&amp;gt; folder 1 (within my documents)
          -&amp;gt; folder 2 (within folder 1)
              -&amp;gt; file B (within folder 2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;directories&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Directories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Directories are the cataloguing system describing where files and folders are stored; also called addresses. Directories take the form of an address like “C:/documents/folder/file” which tells a program to look in this location. The concept of folders and files comes from the days before computers where information was written on paper and stored in filing cabinets. Directories are not case sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recommend that you organise your files in a structured way. For example, have a folder for the module and sub-folders for each of the practicals:&lt;br /&gt;
Documents (folder) -&amp;gt; Biostats (folder) -&amp;gt; Practical 1 (folder) -&amp;gt; Script (file)&lt;br /&gt;
We don’t recommend using a automatically selected “downloads” folder or your “desktop” because these are not permanent file locations and can be hard to find files later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the components of the address is separated using a forward slash &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt;. R can understand &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; but does not understand back slash &lt;code&gt;\&lt;/code&gt; because back slashes have a specific meaning in programming. When typing addresses, make sure you use the correct slash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We navigate through our computer’s directories using Explorer in Windows or Finder in MacOS. You can see the address of a directory in the address bar. We will learn how to use directories in RStudio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why R?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R is just one of &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; high-level programming languages used professionally (e.g. C++, Java, Python) but R is specially designed for doing statistics and data handling. Hence R is widely taught in statistic classes. There are other statistics programs but these are normally “point-and-click” programs where you click a button and magic happens. The reasons we use R are that it is an open source software and it is &lt;em&gt;transparent&lt;/em&gt;, meaning you can &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; how your data is being manipulated. Transparency allows us to check whether the statistics is done correctly and is easier to see how statistical theory is being applied. R is also &lt;em&gt;reproducible&lt;/em&gt; because R allows you to document your code in &lt;em&gt;scripts&lt;/em&gt; that you can give another person to replicate your analysis. The traditional option is to learn these calculations by hand and use pre-calculated statistical reference tables but we would only expect that for very simple examples and doing calculations by hand is an arduous task for realistic biological problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;why-rstudio&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why RStudio?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R and RStudio are different software. R is a computer programming language and statistical environment. RStudio is a user interface which has some useful features that makes using R easier. It is possible to use R by itself (you can try it) but RStudio makes everything a lot easier by providing some organisation. You cannot use RStudio without R. An analogy is that R is the engine of a car and RStudio is the steering wheel - you control the wheel but the engine is what makes the car go forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;installing-r-and-rstudio&#34; class=&#34;section level1 tabset&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installing R and RStudio&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need to install R AND RStudio &lt;strong&gt;in that order&lt;/strong&gt;. You only need to open RStudio when you want to use R - RStudio will open R for you in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;CRANsite.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video about installing R &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/203516510&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/203516510&lt;/a&gt; and RStudio &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/203516968&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://vimeo.com/203516968&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can follow the instructions below or try the interactive tutorial at &lt;a href=&#34;https://learnr-examples.shinyapps.io/ex-setup-r/#section-welcome&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://learnr-examples.shinyapps.io/ex-setup-r/#section-welcome&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the instructions for various operating software:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;windows&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Windows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For R:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/bin/windows/base/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/bin/windows/base/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click “Download R” in the blue box. The version number is not important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the file, open it and follow the instructions. You can leave everything as the default option. Make sure you’ve installed the program somewhere sensible like the Programs folder in the C:/ drive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open it and check it installed properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For RStudio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click download for &lt;strong&gt;RStudio Desktop Open Source Licence&lt;/strong&gt;. The FREE option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the program somewhere sensible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open it and check it installed properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mac&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mac&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For R:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click “Download R for (Mac) OS X”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the latest release file (e.g. R-4.0.2.pkg), open it and follow the instructions. You can leave everything as the default option. Make sure you’ve installed the program somewhere sensible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open it and check it installed properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For RStudio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click download for &lt;strong&gt;RStudio Desktop Open Source Licence&lt;/strong&gt;. The FREE option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install the program somewhere sensible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open it and check it installed properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;linux&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Linux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For R:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click “Download R for Linux”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click your version of Linux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy and paste the relevant installation code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open R and check it installed properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For RStudio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click download for &lt;strong&gt;RStudio Desktop Open Source Licence&lt;/strong&gt;. The FREE option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the relevant code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open it and check it installed properly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://linuxconfig.org/rstudio-on-ubuntu-18-04-bionic-beaver-linux&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://linuxconfig.org/rstudio-on-ubuntu-18-04-bionic-beaver-linux&lt;/a&gt; for a guide&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;chromebook&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chromebook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The easiest option is to run Linux on your computer, then you can install R and RStudio. Try the instructions on &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.sellorm.com/2018/12/20/installing-r-and-rstudio-on-a-chromebook/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://blog.sellorm.com/2018/12/20/installing-r-and-rstudio-on-a-chromebook/&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jennybc/operation-chromebook#links-re-r-and-rstudio&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/jennybc/operation-chromebook#links-re-r-and-rstudio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use RStudio Server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use RStudio Cloud &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.cloud/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://rstudio.cloud/&lt;/a&gt; (in beta so it may not work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry chromebook users, if your chromebook version is very old then it may not be possible to install R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;opening-r-and-rstudio-for-the-first-time&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Opening R and RStudio for the first time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you open R itself you’ll see that it’s pretty bare bones. Most annoyingly you have to remember what information is stored in its memory. RStudio is a intermediate program that acts as a mediator between you and R:&lt;br /&gt;
user -&amp;gt; input -&amp;gt; RStudio -&amp;gt; R -&amp;gt; RStudio -&amp;gt; output -&amp;gt; user&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you open RStudio you’ll see several windows that organise how information is passed to R and how output from R is presented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;RStudio-console.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left: The big window is the &lt;strong&gt;console&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the interface with R and is the same as using R on its own. (don’t worry about “terminal”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top right: This window has three tabs: “environment” - shows you what information is stored in R’s memory, “history” - shows your code history &amp;amp; “connections” - don’t worry about this one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bottom right: This has several tabs. The most important being “files” - showing you where RStudio is looking at on your computer &amp;amp; “plot” - shows you any plots you make in R.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can customise the layout and colour scheme of RStudio in Options.&lt;br /&gt;
There are other user interfaces for R but RStudio has a lot of support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;updating-r-and-packages&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Updating R and packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last major update to R was version 4.0. If you have an older version we recommending updating R because many fundamental aspects of the language were changed and are not backwards compatible. You will see which R version is used in the information in the Console when you open RStudio. If your version is older than 4.0, install the latest version as above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R is a statistical environment that consist of &lt;strong&gt;packages&lt;/strong&gt;. Packages are a set of &lt;strong&gt;functions&lt;/strong&gt; that does something to input depending on the underlying code. All your packages are stored in your &lt;strong&gt;library&lt;/strong&gt;. When you download R it comes with a basic set of packages as default which works straight out of the box. This is called &lt;strong&gt;base R&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve installed R you should check all your &lt;strong&gt;packages&lt;/strong&gt; are up to date as well. You can update your packages by clicking the Update button under the Packages tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can customise and expand the functionality of R by installing more packages, which are made by people and distributed freely. You can download packages from an online repository using the function &lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#34;&amp;lt;insert name of package&amp;gt;&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;. For example, I wrote this document in RStudio using an additional package called &lt;code&gt;rmarkdown&lt;/code&gt; which lets me make HTML, word or PDF files of text, code and figures or tables. We will tell you if you need to install a package but where possible we will be sticking to base R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;creating-a-script&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating a script&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest advantage of RStudio is that it allows you to write &lt;strong&gt;scripts&lt;/strong&gt;. These are files ending in &lt;code&gt;.R&lt;/code&gt; that are created and opened by RStudio. R itself cannot open, read or create scripts. Scripts are text documents of code that you can save on your computer and open later. They provide a guide to what you want to enter to R and saves you from &lt;strong&gt;having to type out code over and over again&lt;/strong&gt;. Before RStudio, we had to save our code in notepad or similar then copy and paste it into R (believe me it was a pain). Now we can do the same but in one click. Importantly, scripts allow &lt;strong&gt;reproducibility&lt;/strong&gt; and helps with problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create a new script under File -&amp;gt; New file -&amp;gt; Script (Ctrl+Shift+N) or click the white square with a green and white plus sign in the top left corner.&lt;br /&gt;
Save it and give it an informative name (e.g. “Dropin1.R”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;open-script.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s add some code to this script by going through the basics of R! Copy and paste code from below into your script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run code from your script rather than directly from the console&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A script is a record of what you’ve done and it makes it easy to spot any mistakes you might have made (transparency &amp;amp; reproducibility). Put your cursor on the line you want to run then press Ctrl+Enter or click Run. You can run multiple lines by highlighting the relevant lines. You can run the entire script from beginning to end using the shortcut Ctrl+Alt+R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Run.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;setting-up-packages&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting up packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use a package in R, you need to &lt;strong&gt;call&lt;/strong&gt; it from R’s library using the function &lt;code&gt;library()&lt;/code&gt;. A package we will see later in the module is &lt;code&gt;MASS&lt;/code&gt; which contains datasets you can use at home to practice the statistical tests covered in the lectures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type &lt;code&gt;library(MASS)&lt;/code&gt; into your script then press Enter. You have just &lt;strong&gt;run&lt;/strong&gt; your first line of code. R will load the package &lt;code&gt;MASS&lt;/code&gt; in the background. You can check this in RStudio under the Packages tab where there will now be a tick in the box next to &lt;code&gt;MASS&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;data()&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;data(package = .packages(all.available = TRUE))&lt;/code&gt; to see the list of available built-in datasets. Some of these will be relevant to biological sciences, others are more general (e.g. the starwars dataset of Star Wars characters comes with the package &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;). Entering the name of a dataset will display the entire dataset. Try calling one of the &lt;code&gt;MASS&lt;/code&gt; datasets, like &lt;code&gt;Rabbit&lt;/code&gt;. You can see the descriptions of each dataset by calling &lt;code&gt;help(&amp;lt;dataset name&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;, e.g. &lt;code&gt;help(Rabbit)&lt;/code&gt; will tell you it describes the blood pressure of rabbits before and after a drug treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;working-directories&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Working directories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember directories? Typing out whole addresses starting from the hard drive is annoying. There is a short cut if we use &lt;strong&gt;working directories&lt;/strong&gt;. Working directories are default directories that programs will look in first. We can then use directory address that are &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; to this default address which shortens addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, following this directory structure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;C:
  -&amp;gt; documents
      -&amp;gt; file A 
      -&amp;gt; folder 1 
          -&amp;gt; folder 2 
              -&amp;gt; file B&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the default directory is C:/, then the address for file B is &lt;code&gt;C:/documents/folder1/folder2/fileB&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
But if we set folder 1 as the working directory &lt;code&gt;C:/documents/folder1/&lt;/code&gt;, then we can use the relative address for the file: &lt;code&gt;folder2/fileB&lt;/code&gt;. This way we don’t have to type &lt;code&gt;C:/documents/folder1/&lt;/code&gt; every time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Navigating through directories using addresses can be confusing. Another useful command is &lt;code&gt;..&lt;/code&gt; which tells the address to go &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt; a directory. For example, if folder 2 was the working directory &lt;code&gt;C:/documents/folder1/folder2&lt;/code&gt; and we wanted to access file A, then we need to tell the computer to go up two directories. The relative address for the file is: &lt;code&gt;../../fileA&lt;/code&gt; which means that the computer is now looking in the &lt;code&gt;documents&lt;/code&gt; folder. In contrast, the relative address for file B is even shorter, &lt;code&gt;fileB&lt;/code&gt;, since folder 2 is already the working directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RStudio has a default working directory.&lt;br /&gt;
You can see which working directory is the default directory in RStudio on the “Files” tab. You can also check what working directory R is using by typing &lt;code&gt;getwd()&lt;/code&gt; (GET Working Directory). When you run code directly from the Console, it will use the RStudio working directory. The working directory of a script by default is the directory the script is saved in - this may be different to the default working directory in the Files tab. &lt;em&gt;This may be one reason RStudio cannot find a file even with a “correct” relative address&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;changing-working-directories&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Changing working directories&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can change the default RStudio directory under Tools -&amp;gt; Global Options but on a daily basis, changing the directory temporarily under Session -&amp;gt; Set working directory is more useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need to know how to change working directories and tell R where to find files through relative addresses because that is how we &lt;strong&gt;import&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;export&lt;/strong&gt; data to and from R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;setwd.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The R function to do the same thing is &lt;code&gt;setwd()&lt;/code&gt; (SET Working Directory). e.g. &lt;code&gt;setwd(&amp;lt;insert directory address here&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;. It is good practice to keep similar files in the same folder. Otherwise you will need to specify the full address when you call a file that exists in another folder and it can get confusing if your files are all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of directories and addresses like postal addresses - if your address is incorrect the postman (R) wouldn’t know where to go to pick up your parcel (file). If R cannot find a file, check the address or the working directory is correct&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;loading-data&#34; class=&#34;section level1 tabset&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Loading data&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use data stored in other files, the data must be &lt;strong&gt;loaded&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;read&lt;/strong&gt; into R. Imported data &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; be assigned a name (using &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/code&gt;) or it won’t be saved to R’s memory. The &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; functions are a set of base R function that import data based on how data is saved in the file. In this module we will focus on two types of storing data: tab delimated &amp;amp; comma separated values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In tab deliminated data, values are separated by tabs. e.g. 1 2 3 4 5 6 (separated by 1 space). The &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; function is &lt;code&gt;read.delim()&lt;/code&gt; for deliminated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In comma separated values data (CSV), values are separated by commas. e.g. 1,2,3,4,5. The &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; function is &lt;code&gt;read.csv()&lt;/code&gt; for CSV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Files names or directories are designated as character strings (&lt;code&gt;&#34;&#34;&lt;/code&gt;). &lt;code&gt;read.table()&lt;/code&gt; also works for tables. See &lt;code&gt;help(&#34;read.table&#34;)&lt;/code&gt; for the general inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; functions have two important settings to be aware of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;header&lt;/code&gt;: Use &lt;code&gt;header = FALSE&lt;/code&gt; (default) if your data doesn’t have headers, &lt;code&gt;header = TRUE&lt;/code&gt; to force R to recognise headers - usually the first row of data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sep&lt;/code&gt;: Tells R to recognise how individual observations are separated (hence sep). &lt;code&gt;sep = &#34;&#34;&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;sep = &#34; &#34;&lt;/code&gt; if it’s tab separated data (with white spaces between data - &lt;code&gt;&#34;&#34;&lt;/code&gt; is a general indicator for any whitespace, &lt;code&gt;&#34; &#34;&lt;/code&gt; is specifically 1 space) or &lt;code&gt;sep = &#34;,&#34;&lt;/code&gt; for comma separated values. If the data didn’t import properly it could be because the wrong read function or the wrong separator was used - try another one. Most of the time the default will be fine, which means you do not have to manually specify these settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always&lt;/strong&gt; check that your data loaded properly. We expect you to be able to load data from file or from clipboard during practicals and assessment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes strings are loaded as factors instead of characters or vice versa. Sometimes the columns are not recognised because the separator character is incorrect. There are always simple solutions to these problems (e.g. a small typo) and you should be able to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s practice two ways of importing data using &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; functions: from a file and from the clipboard. The relevant files are available on Blackboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;txt&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;.txt&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text files (.txt) tend to be delimited, meaning information is separated by a space of fixed width. This is loaded using &lt;code&gt;read.delim()&lt;/code&gt;. Try loading the file “small_sleep.txt” to an R element called &lt;code&gt;small_sleep&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;small_sleep &amp;lt;- read.delim(&amp;quot;small_sleep.txt&amp;quot;)
small_sleep
                  Species   BodyWt TotalSleep
1         Africanelephant 6654.000        3.3
2  Africangiantpouchedrat    1.000        8.3
3               ArcticFox    3.385       12.5
4    Arcticgroundsquirrel    0.920       16.5
5           Asianelephant 2547.000        3.9
6                  Baboon   10.550        9.8
7             Bigbrownbat    0.023       19.7
8          Braziliantapir  160.000        6.2
9                     Cat    3.300       14.5
10             Chimpanzee   52.160        9.7&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;csv&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;.csv&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If data is separated by a comma, it’s called a comma separated value file (.csv). Note that .txt files can also be comma separated. The function to read csv is &lt;code&gt;read.csv()&lt;/code&gt;. Try loading the file “mammal_sleep.csv” to an R element called &lt;code&gt;mammal_sleep&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mammal_sleep &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;mammal_sleep.csv&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data collected in Excel can be saved as a .csv file using the Save As option. CSV is preferred in many instances over the default Excel file type because it is less prone to error. This is what we will mostly be using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;copying-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Copying data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Clipboard is where your computer saves information that you’ve copied using ctrl/cmd + c.&lt;br /&gt;
For quick and dirty data entry, or for copying code from the Internet, you can load data from the clipboard after highlighting data and copying it. You cannot paste data directly into R. But it is always better to save a data file as a .csv file and importing into R so you always have a copy of the raw data you used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;clip.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For PC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;myclip_data &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;clipboard&amp;quot;) # also works with read.delim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mac:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;myclip_data &amp;lt;- read.csv(pipe(&amp;quot;pbpaste&amp;quot;)) # also works with read.delim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web browsers might display tabbed whitespace differently so try a different separator depending on what web browser you are using (see above). If all else fails, copy the data into Excel and save the file (problem solving!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;try-it-yourself&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Try it yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For whichever operating system you have, highlight and copy this data and load this data into R using you new R script. Make sure you are using the correct &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                  Species   BodyWt
1         Africanelephant 6654.000
2  Africangiantpouchedrat    1.000
3               ArcticFox    3.385
4    Arcticgroundsquirrel    0.920
5           Asianelephant 2547.000
6                  Baboon   10.550
7             Bigbrownbat    0.023
8          Braziliantapir  160.000
9                     Cat    3.300
10             Chimpanzee   52.160&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Species,BodyWt,BrainWt,NonDreaming,Dreaming,TotalSleep,LifeSpan,Gestation,Predation,Exposure,Danger
Africanelephant,6654,5712,NA,NA,3.3,38.6,645,3,5,3
Africangiantpouchedrat,1,6.6,6.3,2,8.3,4.5,42,3,1,3
ArcticFox,3.385,44.5,NA,NA,12.5,14,60,1,1,1
Arcticgroundsquirrel,0.92,5.7,NA,NA,16.5,NA,25,5,2,3
Asianelephant,2547,4603,2.1,1.8,3.9,69,624,3,5,4
Baboon,10.55,179.5,9.1,0.7,9.8,27,180,4,4,4
Bigbrownbat,0.023,0.3,15.8,3.9,19.7,19,35,1,1,1
Braziliantapir,160,169,5.2,1,6.2,30.4,392,4,5,4
Cat,3.3,25.6,10.9,3.6,14.5,28,63,1,2,1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;checking-the-data&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Checking the data&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always&lt;/strong&gt; check that your data loaded properly. Sometimes strings are loaded as factors instead of characters or vice versa. Sometimes the columns are not recognised because the separator character is incorrect. There are always simple solutions to these problems (e.g. a small typo) and you should be able to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For bigger datasets it is easier to view a subset of the data or to use the &lt;code&gt;View()&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;head(mammal_sleep, n = 6) # View the first 6 rows (6 is default, can be changed)
                 Species   BodyWt BrainWt NonDreaming Dreaming TotalSleep
1        Africanelephant 6654.000  5712.0          NA       NA        3.3
2 Africangiantpouchedrat    1.000     6.6         6.3      2.0        8.3
3              ArcticFox    3.385    44.5          NA       NA       12.5
4   Arcticgroundsquirrel    0.920     5.7          NA       NA       16.5
5          Asianelephant 2547.000  4603.0         2.1      1.8        3.9
6                 Baboon   10.550   179.5         9.1      0.7        9.8
  LifeSpan Gestation Predation Exposure Danger
1     38.6       645         3        5      3
2      4.5        42         3        1      3
3     14.0        60         1        1      1
4       NA        25         5        2      3
5     69.0       624         3        5      4
6     27.0       180         4        4      4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;View(mammal_sleep)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;data-structure&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;str()&lt;/code&gt; is a handy function for checking the structure of your dataset. Let’s check the mammal sleep dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;str(mammal_sleep)
&amp;#39;data.frame&amp;#39;:   62 obs. of  11 variables:
 $ Species    : chr  &amp;quot;Africanelephant&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Africangiantpouchedrat&amp;quot; &amp;quot;ArcticFox&amp;quot; &amp;quot;Arcticgroundsquirrel&amp;quot; ...
 $ BodyWt     : num  6654 1 3.38 0.92 2547 ...
 $ BrainWt    : num  5712 6.6 44.5 5.7 4603 ...
 $ NonDreaming: num  NA 6.3 NA NA 2.1 9.1 15.8 5.2 10.9 8.3 ...
 $ Dreaming   : num  NA 2 NA NA 1.8 0.7 3.9 1 3.6 1.4 ...
 $ TotalSleep : num  3.3 8.3 12.5 16.5 3.9 9.8 19.7 6.2 14.5 9.7 ...
 $ LifeSpan   : num  38.6 4.5 14 NA 69 27 19 30.4 28 50 ...
 $ Gestation  : num  645 42 60 25 624 180 35 392 63 230 ...
 $ Predation  : int  3 3 1 5 3 4 1 4 1 1 ...
 $ Exposure   : int  5 1 1 2 5 4 1 5 2 1 ...
 $ Danger     : int  3 3 1 3 4 4 1 4 1 1 ...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first line tells us that &lt;code&gt;mammal_sleep&lt;/code&gt; is a data frame. Which is how R stores observations in rows and columns. Other types are lists and matrices. It also tells us there are 62 observations - meaning the number of rows of data - and 11 variables - meaning the number of columns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the first column of &lt;code&gt;str()&lt;/code&gt;, are the names of the columns of the dataset listed with an &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; are . So the first column is called &lt;code&gt;Species&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second column shows what &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; of variable the data are: character (&lt;code&gt;chr&lt;/code&gt;) for letters, numeric (&lt;code&gt;num&lt;/code&gt;) for continuous numbers and integer (&lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt;) for discrete numbers. Another type you will encounter are &lt;code&gt;Factors&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;levels&lt;/code&gt; - these are categorical variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third column shows the first couple of observations in each column&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;summarising-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summarising data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary()&lt;/code&gt; shows some summary statistics for the specific variable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;summary(mammal_sleep) # for all columns
   Species              BodyWt            BrainWt         NonDreaming    
 Length:62          Min.   :   0.005   Min.   :   0.14   Min.   : 2.100  
 Class :character   1st Qu.:   0.600   1st Qu.:   4.25   1st Qu.: 6.250  
 Mode  :character   Median :   3.342   Median :  17.25   Median : 8.350  
                    Mean   : 198.790   Mean   : 283.13   Mean   : 8.673  
                    3rd Qu.:  48.202   3rd Qu.: 166.00   3rd Qu.:11.000  
                    Max.   :6654.000   Max.   :5712.00   Max.   :17.900  
                                                         NA&amp;#39;s   :14      
    Dreaming       TotalSleep       LifeSpan         Gestation     
 Min.   :0.000   Min.   : 2.60   Min.   :  2.000   Min.   : 12.00  
 1st Qu.:0.900   1st Qu.: 8.05   1st Qu.:  6.625   1st Qu.: 35.75  
 Median :1.800   Median :10.45   Median : 15.100   Median : 79.00  
 Mean   :1.972   Mean   :10.53   Mean   : 19.878   Mean   :142.35  
 3rd Qu.:2.550   3rd Qu.:13.20   3rd Qu.: 27.750   3rd Qu.:207.50  
 Max.   :6.600   Max.   :19.90   Max.   :100.000   Max.   :645.00  
 NA&amp;#39;s   :12      NA&amp;#39;s   :4       NA&amp;#39;s   :4         NA&amp;#39;s   :4       
   Predation        Exposure         Danger     
 Min.   :1.000   Min.   :1.000   Min.   :1.000  
 1st Qu.:2.000   1st Qu.:1.000   1st Qu.:1.000  
 Median :3.000   Median :2.000   Median :2.000  
 Mean   :2.871   Mean   :2.419   Mean   :2.613  
 3rd Qu.:4.000   3rd Qu.:4.000   3rd Qu.:4.000  
 Max.   :5.000   Max.   :5.000   Max.   :5.000  
                                                
summary(mammal_sleep$BodyWt) # summary statistics for body weight
    Min.  1st Qu.   Median     Mean  3rd Qu.     Max. 
   0.005    0.600    3.342  198.790   48.202 6654.000 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;tips&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Tips&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coding is like learning a language. There is grammar, syntax and terminology to learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The secret to being a coding whiz is practice, practice, practice. Try using R at every opportunity. If you don’t use it, you lose it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s OK to google everything. No matter how many years you’ve been using R you will forget something basic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of programming is logic. If you can’t describe what you want to achieve in words, then you can’t code it. Sometimes the solution means changing your way of thinking about a problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lot of errors come from spelling or syntax mistakes. It doesn’t mean you don’t know it, check your code carefully for typos. Missing brackets or quotation marks are common mistakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often, copying and pasting your error message into google comes up with the solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trial and error is a big part of programming. If it doesn’t work the first time, tweak it and try it again. Getting a function to work might be as simple as adding or removing one of the defined parameters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;finding-help&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Finding help&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All R code comes with help files. You can access them from the “Help” tab in RStudio. If you want help on a specific function, then you can type in &lt;code&gt;help(&amp;lt;insert function name here&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt;. If you don’t know your exact query, you can search using &lt;code&gt;??&amp;lt;insert term here&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; - e.g. &lt;code&gt;??mean&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Internet is really really great for R help. Websites like StackExchange are help forums for programming. Most likely your question has already been answered on StackExchange. The trick is knowing what to type into Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning to problem solve independently is not something you learn by reading or something you can be taught. It is a skill you have to learn by &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt;, which means having a go yourself before seeking help from others. Make asking for help your last option. You’ll see on StackExchange people &lt;em&gt;describe&lt;/em&gt; what they want to achieve, what they have done so far, identified what the problem is and provide some reproducible code to help someone else understand their problem. It’s really hard to fix someone’s coding problem without context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;final-checklist&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Final checklist&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed R?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed RStudio?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are all your versions and packages up to date?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know how to create and save an R script?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know how to set your working directory?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you import data into R?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you run a line of code?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you use a function?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to add a Phylopic icon to your graph in R</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-08-01-rphylopic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-08-01-rphylopic/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-08-01-rphylopic/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;phylopic.org&#34;&gt;Phylopic&lt;/a&gt; is an online database of silhouettes of species. Most are freely available, with various copyright licences. It’s a great resource for scientific illustration or making cool presentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way I wanted to use Phylopic was to add a silhouette of an animal directly to an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; figure. You could search Phylopic yourself and copy the image id to add the icon to the graph but where’s the fun in that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/rphylopic/readme/README.html&#34;&gt;rphylopic&lt;/a&gt; is an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; package that can search and retrieve icons directly from Phylopic. You can use &lt;code&gt;rphylopic&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; or base graphics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of searching Phylopic and pulling out the image id is not straightforward, and I didn’t find a step-by-step guide I liked for doing so, so here is a reproducible example using the built in dataset &lt;code&gt;beaver1&lt;/code&gt; - a time series of a beaver’s body temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data looks like this and we want to add a beaver icon to the top left corner:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;beaver_plot &amp;lt;- qplot(beaver1$temp,x = seq_along(beaver1$temp), geom = &amp;quot;line&amp;quot;, xlab = &amp;quot;Time&amp;quot;, ylab = &amp;quot;Temperature&amp;quot;)
beaver_plot&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-08-01-rphylopic/index_files/figure-html/beaver-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;step-by-step-guide-to-adding-a-phylopic-icon&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Step-by-step guide to adding a Phylopic icon&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;getting-the-right-species&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Getting the right species&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can search Phylopic by species using &lt;code&gt;name_search&lt;/code&gt;. You might get multiple hits because there may be multiple matches in the databases. It’s worth cross-referencing the NameBank ID with the website. The NameBank ID is located at the top right of the webpage. In this case we want the first option - 109179.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(rphylopic)
beaver &amp;lt;- name_search(text = &amp;quot;Castor canadensis&amp;quot;, options = &amp;quot;namebankID&amp;quot;)[[1]] # find names
beaver&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;extracting-the-id-of-the-icon-you-want&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Extracting the id of the icon you want&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;name_images&lt;/code&gt; to list all the beaver icons available. In this case, there are two versions of the beaver icon we can use - listed as &lt;code&gt;$same[[1]]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$same[[2]]&lt;/code&gt; with unique &lt;code&gt;uid&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;uid&lt;/code&gt; is the unique id of the icon. Again, it’s handy to check the &lt;code&gt;uid&lt;/code&gt; with the website. You can find the &lt;code&gt;uid&lt;/code&gt; on the website by clicking the actual icon you want to use and copying from the address bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;beaver_id_all &amp;lt;- name_images(uuid = beaver$uid[1])  # list images
beaver_id_all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s use the second icon and extract only that &lt;code&gt;uid&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;beaver_id &amp;lt;- name_images(uuid = beaver$uid[1])$same[[2]]$uid  # get individual image id
beaver_id&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;getting-the-icon-itself&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Getting the icon itself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can get the actual image using &lt;code&gt;image_data&lt;/code&gt;. Each icon is available in different sizes, from a thumbnail (64 px) to large icons (1042 px). We will get a 256 px icon so that the resolution is high enough to avoid pixelation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;beaver_pic &amp;lt;- image_data(beaver_id, size = 256)[[1]] # get actual icon, define size. Don&amp;#39;t run this alone&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;adding-the-beaver-icon-to-the-plot&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Adding the beaver icon to the plot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;add_phylopic&lt;/code&gt; to add the icon to a &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; graph. You need to specify the x and y axis co-ordinates for the graph. Use &lt;code&gt;ysize&lt;/code&gt; to change the size of the icon. Use &lt;code&gt;alpha&lt;/code&gt; to control the transparency. &lt;code&gt;colour&lt;/code&gt; will change the colour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;beaver_plot + add_phylopic(beaver_pic, alpha = 1, x = 10, y = 37.4, ysize = 10)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;featured.png&#34; style=&#34;width:70.0%&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The final plot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! 🦫&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;other-uses-of-rphylopic&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Other uses of &lt;code&gt;rphylopic&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can add the icon as a background image but I would question why that would be a good idea from a graphic design perspective. To do so, you don’t need to specify any other variables in &lt;code&gt;add_phylopic&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can also use icons as data points by plotting each icon in place of the regular point within a for loop. You can see an example in the &lt;code&gt;rphylopic&lt;/code&gt; documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OSM in R</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-07-01-OSM-in-R/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-07-01-OSM-in-R/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-07-01-OSM-in-R/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This tutorial was originally presented to NERD club on 4/2/2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;city-maps&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;City maps&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider yourself a hipster?&lt;br /&gt;
Do the clean lines and natural materials of modern scandi make you feel at home?&lt;br /&gt;
Is your basic coffee order a flat white? ☕&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the answer to all the above is YES, then here’s a present for you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://images-na.ssl-images-amazon.com/images/I/61-dKVczbXL._SL1000_.jpg&#34; title=&#34;fig:&#34; width=&#34;250&#34; alt=&#34;A map of Dublin&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But wait!&lt;/em&gt; This poster costs €30 (thereabouts) online!
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.etsy.com/ie/listing/561937898/dublin-print-dublin-city-map-dublin&#34;&gt;See example&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
That’s approximately 9 flat whites you could have had.&lt;br /&gt;
☕☕☕☕☕☕☕☕☕&lt;br /&gt;
Can you make this in R?, you ask, asking for a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fear not&lt;/strong&gt;. You can make this yourself in R!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;maps-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Maps in R&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this tutorial we will replicate a poster like this. We will need R and powerpoint to put in the final touches. You could do it fully in R but powerpoint will make our lives a bit easier. In summary, it requires a bit of GIS wrangling to code in what you want to display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data is freely available from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openstreetmap.org&#34;&gt;Openstreetmap&lt;/a&gt;, for proprietary haters out there. I will refer to it as OSM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be following &lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2tutor.com/streetmaps/streetmaps/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;setup&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will need to install the relevant packages: &lt;code&gt;osmdata&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sf&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#install.packages(&amp;quot;osmdata&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;tidyverse&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sf&amp;quot;)
library(osmdata)
library(tidyverse)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see this will use tidyverse and I will be using piping. Don’t worry if you are not a master at piping. The code is written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, instead of function2(function1(X)) to apply function 1 &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; function 2 to X, you type x %&amp;gt;% function1() %&amp;gt;% function2(). I.E. take X, apply function 1, then apply function 2 to the resulting output. Overall it’s easier to read, hence it’s ‘tidy’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;osm-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OSM data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OSM stores various features you can explore under &lt;code&gt;available_features()&lt;/code&gt;. You can see what is under each feature with &lt;code&gt;available_tags(&#34;&amp;lt;insert feature name here&amp;gt;&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;get-city-co-ordinates&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1. Get city co-ordinates&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this example we will make a map of Dublin. First we need the latitude and longitude of Dublin. If you want to modify the extent of your map, this is where you change the co-ordinates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;city_coords &amp;lt;- getbb(&amp;quot;Dublin Ireland&amp;quot;)
#city_coords &amp;lt;- c(-6.391,53.2644,-6.114883, 53.416) # to get all the M50&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;get-map-features&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. Get map features&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;roads&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Roads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can get roads by querying OSM for the GPS co-ordinates for Dublin and saving it to a variable called &lt;em&gt;roads&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;roads &amp;lt;- city_coords %&amp;gt;% #pipe!
  opq() %&amp;gt;% # create query for OSM database
  add_osm_feature(key = &amp;quot;highway&amp;quot;, 
                  value = c(&amp;quot;motorway&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;primary&amp;quot;, 
                            &amp;quot;secondary&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;tertiary&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  osmdata_sf() # save it as an simple features format
roads&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;streets&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Streets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do the same for streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;streets &amp;lt;- city_coords%&amp;gt;%
  opq()%&amp;gt;%
  add_osm_feature(key = &amp;quot;highway&amp;quot;, 
                  value = c(&amp;quot;residential&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;living_street&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;unclassified&amp;quot;,
                            &amp;quot;service&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;footway&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  osmdata_sf()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;water&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Water&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can’t forget the Liffey and the canals. Sadly the ocean cannot be mapped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;water &amp;lt;- city_coords%&amp;gt;%
  opq()%&amp;gt;%
  add_osm_feature(key = &amp;quot;waterway&amp;quot;, value = c(&amp;quot;canal&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;river&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  osmdata_sf()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;plotting&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;3. Plotting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to call &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; and plot our map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;map &amp;lt;- ggplot() +
  # roads
  geom_sf(data = roads$osm_lines,
          inherit.aes = FALSE,
          color = &amp;quot;grey&amp;quot;, # colour of feature
          size = 0.8,       # Size on map
          alpha = 0.8) +    # transparency
  # streets
  geom_sf(data = streets$osm_lines,
          inherit.aes = FALSE,
          color = &amp;quot;#ffbe7f&amp;quot;,
          size = 0.2,
          alpha = 0.6) +
  # water
  geom_sf(data = water$osm_lines,
          inherit.aes = FALSE,
          color = &amp;quot;steelblue&amp;quot;,
          size = 0.8,
          alpha = 0.5) +
  # extent to display
  coord_sf(xlim = c(city_coords[1],city_coords[3]),
           ylim = c(city_coords[2],city_coords[4]),
           expand = FALSE) +
  # remove axes
  theme_void()

map&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;labels&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4. Labels&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point it is easier to save the file and add text in powerpoint but if you want to try your hand at ggplot’s annotation features go ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I’ve done one in a dark colour scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;theme_colour &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;#282828&amp;quot; # dark theme

dark_map &amp;lt;- map +
  labs(caption = &amp;quot;Dublin, Ireland&amp;quot;) +
  theme(axis.text = element_blank(),
        plot.margin=unit(c(1,1,1,1),&amp;quot;cm&amp;quot;),
        panel.grid.major = element_line(colour = theme_colour),
        panel.grid.minor = element_line(colour = theme_colour),
        plot.background = element_rect(fill = theme_colour),
        panel.background = element_rect(fill = theme_colour),
        plot.caption = element_text(size = 24, colour = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, hjust = 0.5, vjust = -2, family = &amp;quot;mono&amp;quot;),
        panel.border = element_rect(colour = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, fill=NA, size=2),
        axis.ticks = element_blank())

dark_map&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;saving-our-map&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Saving our map&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggsave(plot = dark_map, filename = &amp;quot;NERD/dark_dublin.pdf&amp;quot;, width = 11, height = 8.5, device = &amp;quot;pdf&amp;quot;, dpi = 300)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all of that was too much, there’s an R package for it. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lina2497/Giftmap&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://github.com/lina2497/Giftmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://anvaka.github.io/city-roads/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;extra-details&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Extra details&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less is more but if you really want to put more features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;other-water-bodies&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other water bodies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;extra_water &amp;lt;- city_coords %&amp;gt;%
  opq()%&amp;gt;%
  add_osm_feature(key = &amp;quot;natural&amp;quot;, value = c(&amp;quot;water&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  osmdata_sf()

dark_map +
   geom_sf(data = extra_water$osm_polygons,
          inherit.aes = FALSE,
          fill = &amp;quot;steelblue&amp;quot;,
          colour = NA,
          alpha = 0.5) +
  geom_sf(data = extra_water$osm_multipolygons,
          inherit.aes = FALSE,
          fill = &amp;quot;steelblue&amp;quot;,
          colour = NA,
          alpha = 0.5) +
  # extent to display
  coord_sf(xlim = c(city_coords[1],city_coords[3]),
           ylim = c(city_coords[2],city_coords[4]),
           expand = FALSE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;parks&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Parks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature reserves including Dublin Bay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;park &amp;lt;- city_coords%&amp;gt;%
  opq()%&amp;gt;%
  add_osm_feature(key = &amp;quot;leisure&amp;quot;, value = c(&amp;quot;park&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  osmdata_sf()

dark_map +
   geom_sf(data = park$osm_polygons,
          inherit.aes = FALSE,
          fill = &amp;quot;darkgreen&amp;quot;,
          colour = NA,
          alpha = 0.3) +
  geom_sf(data = park$osm_multipolygons,
          inherit.aes = FALSE,
          fill = &amp;quot;darkgreen&amp;quot;,
          colour = NA,
          alpha = 0.3) +
  # extent to display
  coord_sf(xlim = c(city_coords[1],city_coords[3]),
           ylim = c(city_coords[2],city_coords[4]),
           expand = FALSE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;end&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;End&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the gist of using OSM in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;. You can use the same code to make any map, e.g. for a paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NERD club tutorials</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/project/NERD-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/project/NERD-club/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/project/NERD-club/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;NERD club is a student-led peer-learning and discussion group for staff and postgraduate students in the Departments of Zoology and Botany at Trinity College Dublin. The group meets weekly for topical discussions about science or academia. There are also sub-groups that are dedicated towards specific topics such as R coding and spatial analysis. These sub-groups are focused towards peer-learning where, postgraduates in particular, are encouraged to share their learning experience and expertise in relevant topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been an active contributor to NERD club and its sub-groups. This page documents some of the outputs I have produced for peer-learning activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;tutorials&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;advanced-r-markdown&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Advanced R markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a short presentation showing some of the more advanced features of R Markdown using the &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; package &lt;code&gt;bookdown&lt;/code&gt; including: numbered sections, cross-referencing, bibliographies, CSS and making a website with the static HTML builder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PDF: &lt;a class=&#34;fas fa-file-pdf&#34; href=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/files/24March2021_Advanced_R_Markdown.pdf&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;interactive-functions-and-loops-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interactive functions and loops in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-06-01-r-function-loops/&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; describes how to make an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; function that asks the user to input values for the function, and how to run a function within a simple for loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;osm-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OSM in R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-07-01-OSM-in-R/&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; describes how to interface with Open Street Maps in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; to make a fancy map you can print and give to someone but the same code can be used to make maps for any purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Club: Functions &amp; Loops</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-06-01-r-function-loops/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-06-01-r-function-loops/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-06-01-r-function-loops/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This tutorial was originally presented to NERD club on 18/11/2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This document contains two examples of functions and an example of how functions can be integrated with loops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;User defined functions take the general form of &lt;code&gt;function(inputs){processing inputs; return(output)}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;predator-prey-interactions&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Predator-Prey interactions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will use a simulation of predator-prey interactions as an example. Predator-prey interactions simulate how many prey a predator can capture after a specific amount of time and for a given density of prey. We use this example with undergraduate biology students to demonstrate statistical modelling, experimental design and collecting data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally we would get students to do this laboratory practical in class by picking up counters and putting them in jars while blindfolded. We can also see whether the use of different types of jars affects the efficiency of the predator. This is the experimental design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Response variable - Number of prey caught (&lt;code&gt;Ha&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Total foraging time - 1 minute, a constant (&lt;code&gt;T&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predictor variables:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prey density - user defined treatments (&lt;code&gt;H&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type of jar used - jar with a lid or no lid (&lt;code&gt;yes&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;no&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally the students will collect data to parameterise the functional response. Instead I’ve created a function that will predict new values of prey captured using a functional response formula that is already parameterised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;an-interactive-function&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;An interactive function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R has some capacity to be interactive. It can ask a user to input variables.
The function &lt;code&gt;functional_response&lt;/code&gt; will return the number of prey captured for a given prey density and type of jar used. The function will ask for these two inputs each time the function is run. Look at the code below and try to understand the different components. Then try running the code yourself with different inputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#### Interactive function
# Simulation of the predator-prey functional response - DO NOT CHANGE
# To run: click Source (cmd or ctrl+shift+S) or Run All (ctrl+alt+r)
# Or source(&amp;quot;&amp;lt;insert file location here&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, echo = FALSE)

functional_response &amp;lt;- function(){
  
  # Introduce the simulation to the user - prints a message
  cat(paste(
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;You have some counters (prey), a piece of A4 paper &amp;amp; a jar.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;You spread the counters randomly on the A4 sheet.&amp;quot;,
    sep=&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;))
  
  # Ask the user for the prey density for the functional response
  prey_density  &amp;lt;- readline(&amp;quot;How many prey counters are used? &amp;quot;) # ask for prey density
  
  # Check the user has inputted a number properly
  if(!grepl(&amp;quot;^[0-9]+$&amp;quot;, prey_density)){ # check whether the input contains numeric characters between 0-9 using regex (regular expressions)
    message(&amp;quot;Please enter an integer&amp;quot;) # If the input is not a number, tell them to do it again
    return(functional_response()) # Return to the beginning of the function and start again
  }
  prey_density &amp;lt;- as.integer(prey_density) # If the prey density input is a number, turn it into an interger
  
  # Ask the user for the type of jar used
  cat(paste(
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;Every second you (the predator) tap the sheet to find and pick up a prey counter while blindfolded.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;You have 1 minute to put as many prey counters as you can in the jar.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;There are two types of jars you can use while handling prey.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;Enter 1 to use a jar with a lid that you have to open and close.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;Enter 2 to use a jar without a lid.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;What type of jar is used?&amp;quot;,
    sep=&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;))
  lid_used &amp;lt;- menu(c(&amp;quot;Lid&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;No Lid&amp;quot;))
  
  # Calculate the number of prey caught (the functional response) based on the user defined input above
  if(lid_used != 0){ # Check that the use has chosen the jar used properly (1 or 2)
    
    # Use this model if using a jar with a lid
    if(lid_used == 1){
      Ha &amp;lt;- (0.2 * prey_density)/(1 + 0.2 * 0.03 * prey_density) 
    }
    
    # Use this model if using a jar without a lid
    if(lid_used == 2){
      Ha &amp;lt;- (0.7 * prey_density)/(1 + 0.7 * 0.05 * prey_density) 
    }
    
    # Add in some variation around the predicted value so that users don&amp;#39;t get the exact parameterised functional response
    Ha &amp;lt;- Ha + sample(seq(-3,3), 1) 
    
    # Make sure there are no negative prey items caught!
    if(Ha &amp;lt; 0){
      Ha &amp;lt;- 0 # Make prey caught 0 if less than 0
    }
    
    # Make sure the number of prey caught doesn&amp;#39;t exceed the number of prey available!
    if(Ha &amp;gt; prey_density){
      Ha &amp;lt;- prey_density # If prey caught is greater than the number of prey available, make it the maximum possible
    }
    
    # Print a message showing the results
    message(&amp;quot;The number of prey caught is &amp;quot;, floor(Ha), &amp;quot;. Well done!&amp;quot;) 
  }
}

# Actually run the function and tell R that it&amp;#39;s interactive 
if(interactive()) functional_response()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The function doesn’t have any inputs in &lt;code&gt;function()&lt;/code&gt; because it will ask the user for them each time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;readline&lt;/code&gt; is the function to ask for a single user input&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;menu&lt;/code&gt; is the function to ask the user to chose from a number of options
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here the option is press 1 to use a jar with a lid or press 2 to use a jar without a lid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are two parameterised functional responses - one for a jar with a lid and one for a jar without a lid&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;floor&lt;/code&gt; is a function to round the number of prey caught to the lowest whole number&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the practical, students will need to run the above function for 10 prey densities, repeated 3 times, for both jar treatments - so 60 times in total. But we don’t have to do that manually - that is what loops are for!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;functions-and-loops&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Functions and loops&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a non-interactive version of the function above. It doesn’t have the printed messages asking for user input. This time, the function needs 3 inputs as indicated by &lt;code&gt;function(prey_density, lid_used, total_time)&lt;/code&gt;: the prey density used, the type of jar used and the total foraging time, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run the code chunk to load the function into the R environment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Functional response function
functional_response &amp;lt;- function(prey_density, lid_used, total_time){
  
  # Check jar type is inputted correctly
  if (!lid_used %in% c(&amp;quot;yes&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;no&amp;quot;)) {
    stop(&amp;quot;Lid used is not inputted correctly. Use &amp;#39;yes&amp;#39; or &amp;#39;no&amp;#39; in all lowercase&amp;quot;)
  }
  if(lid_used == &amp;quot;yes&amp;quot;){
    Ha &amp;lt;- (0.2 * prey_density * total_time)/(1 + 0.2 * 0.03 * prey_density)
  }
  if(lid_used == &amp;quot;no&amp;quot;){
    Ha &amp;lt;- (0.7 * prey_density * total_time)/(1 + 0.7 * 0.05 * prey_density)
  }
  Ha &amp;lt;- Ha + sample(seq(-3,3), 1)
  if(Ha &amp;lt; 0){
    Ha &amp;lt;- 0
  }
  if(Ha &amp;gt; prey_density){
    Ha &amp;lt;- prey_density
  }
  # message(&amp;quot;The number of prey caught is &amp;quot;, floor(Ha))
return(floor(Ha))
  }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function will check that the character vector indicating the type of jar to be used is correct because R is case sensitive. The function will return the number of prey caught &lt;code&gt;Ha&lt;/code&gt; as indicated by &lt;code&gt;return(Ha)&lt;/code&gt;. The function &lt;code&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; specifically tells R to tell us the output, otherwise R will keep it to itself! Only one output is allowed (unless extra steps are taken).
The rest of the function is the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;using-the-functional-response-function-in-a-loop&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Using the functional response function in a loop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s use a loop to do our entire experiment in one go! No manual inputs for us. In fact we can do as many treatments or replicates as we want. Let’s do prey densities between 5 and 100 in increments of 5 and 3 replicates. Since the function inputs are required we can set them up in the environment for the function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Set parameters for the function
total_time &amp;lt;- 1 # total foraging time in minutes
no_treatments &amp;lt;- seq(from = 5, to = 100, by = 5) # prey density treatments between 5 and 100
replications &amp;lt;- 3 # number of replications

# a numeric vector of prey densities for all treatments, jar types and replications 
prey_density &amp;lt;- rep(rep(no_treatments, replications),2) # repeated twice for each jar type

# a character vector of the jar type
lid_used &amp;lt;- sort(rep(c(&amp;quot;no&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;yes&amp;quot;), length(prey_density)/2)) # &amp;quot;yes&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;no&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By setting up the parameters outside the function or loop, we can easily modify the parameters of the function and feed the new values into the loop. This helps us debug and is cleaner and easier to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now for the actual loop itself. We need to be able to store the output of the looped function.
Lists are the fastest way to do so in R because R is designed for lists and matrices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Create an empty list called prey_caught to populate 
prey_caught &amp;lt;- list()

for(i in seq_along(prey_density)){
  # Run the functional response for the nth observation in the vector prey_density representing all our observations and save it to the list
  prey_caught[[i]] &amp;lt;- functional_response(prey_density = prey_density[i],
                                         lid_used = lid_used[i],
                                         total_time = total_time)
  
  # Prepare the list for further analysis
  prey_caught[[i]] &amp;lt;-  cbind(prey_caught[[i]], prey_density[i]) # add a column for the prey density used to calculate the number of prey caught for that observation (row)
  prey_caught[[i]] &amp;lt;-  cbind(prey_caught[[i]], 1/prey_caught[[i]]) # add a column for the inverse of the number of prey caught - for statiscally parameterising the functional response
  prey_caught[[i]][,3] &amp;lt;-  ifelse(prey_caught[[i]][,3] == Inf, 0, prey_caught[[i]][,3]) # Housekeeping - turn undefined values of prey caught (from calculating 1 divided by 0) into 0. If the number of prey caught was 0
}

# Turn our list into a data frame
prey_caught &amp;lt;- data.frame(do.call(&amp;quot;rbind&amp;quot;, prey_caught))

# Label the columns
colnames(prey_caught) &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;Ha&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;H&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;Ha.1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;HT.1&amp;quot;) # &amp;quot;.1 is inversed columns&amp;quot;

# Add type of lid used to our data frame
prey_caught$lid_used &amp;lt;- lid_used&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here we are using a &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop with the n&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; observation denoted &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt;. This can be called anything you want but &lt;code&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; is from mathematical notation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;seq_along&lt;/code&gt; is a useful function for telling which observation you are at for a vector - try it out on its own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lists can only contain one variable type, unlike a data frame, but that’s why they are fast and memory efficient for high performance computing
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we were to add the jar type (a character vector) to the list within the loop, then all our numeric output will be converted to characters (default R behaviour) - not what we want!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;do.call&lt;/code&gt; is a handy function for lists. It collapses multidimensional lists into one dimension, here appending them by rows (i.e. adding new observations by rows at the end)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;visualising-the-data&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Visualising the data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can plot our results and conduct our linear regression:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)

prey_caught %&amp;gt;% # Absolute values
  ggplot(aes(H, Ha, colour = lid_used)) +
  geom_point() +
  geom_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;, se = FALSE, fullrange=TRUE) +
  labs(x = expression(paste(&amp;quot;Prey density  (H)&amp;quot;)),
       y = expression(paste(&amp;quot;Prey captured  (Ha)&amp;quot;)),
       colour = &amp;quot;Jar used&amp;quot;) +
  theme_classic()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-06-01-r-function-loops/index_files/figure-html/plot-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Linear model
summary(lm(Ha.1 ~ HT.1 * lid_used, prey_caught))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Call:
lm(formula = Ha.1 ~ HT.1 * lid_used, data = prey_caught)

Residuals:
     Min       1Q   Median       3Q      Max 
-0.27245 -0.05371 -0.01596  0.00899  0.84476 

Coefficients:
                 Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)   
(Intercept)       0.07136    0.02262   3.155  0.00204 **
HT.1              1.00548    0.40029   2.512  0.01338 * 
lid_usedyes       0.09517    0.03198   2.976  0.00356 **
HT.1:lid_usedyes -1.11833    0.56609  -1.976  0.05058 . 
---
Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1

Residual standard error: 0.1351 on 116 degrees of freedom
Multiple R-squared:  0.08913,   Adjusted R-squared:  0.06558 
F-statistic: 3.784 on 3 and 116 DF,  p-value: 0.01242&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has saved us from running the code 120 times! Now we can do it in one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Formatting P values</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-05-01-formatting-p-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-05-01-formatting-p-values/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-05-01-formatting-p-values/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-bloggers.com/2016/03/correctly-reporting-p-values-in-summary-tables-reported-with-xtable/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on R bloggers describes a handy function for formatting really small P values in ANOVA tables (more than 3 decimal places) with &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(&amp;lt;0.001\)&lt;/span&gt;. I find this easier to read when I need to present a formatted table, e.g. in teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original function doesn’t cover all ways of creating ANOVA tables in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; so I have extended the function to cover more cases. The &lt;code&gt;fixp&lt;/code&gt; function below will work for ANOVA tables (&lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt;) generated by &lt;code&gt;anova(lm(...))&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;summary(aov(lm(...)))&lt;/code&gt;, as well as the model coefficients table generated by &lt;code&gt;coef(summary(lm(...)))&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-function-to-format-p-values&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A function to format P values&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;fixp &amp;lt;- function(x, dig=3){

# Convert to a data frame
  if(is.data.frame(x) | is.matrix(x)){
  x &amp;lt;- as.data.frame(x)
  } else {
  x &amp;lt;- as.data.frame(x[[1]])
  }

# Check column order  
  if(substr(names(x)[ncol(x)],1,2) != &amp;quot;Pr&amp;quot;){
    warning(&amp;quot;The name of the last column didn&amp;#39;t start with Pr. This may indicate that p-values weren&amp;#39;t in the last row, and thus, that this function is inappropriate.&amp;quot;)
    }
    
# Round P values to &amp;quot;dig&amp;quot; decimal places, default 3     
  x[,ncol(x)] &amp;lt;- round(x[,ncol(x)], dig)

#  
  for(i in 1:nrow(x)){
    if(x[i,ncol(x)] == 0 &amp;amp; !is.na(x[i,ncol(x)])){
      x[i,ncol(x)] &amp;lt;- paste0(&amp;quot;&amp;lt;0.&amp;quot;, paste0(rep(0,dig-1), collapse=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;), &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;)
      }
  }
  x
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main modification to the original function is to expand the conversion of &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; to a data frame to accept lists and matrices. &lt;code&gt;summary(aov(lm(...)))&lt;/code&gt; creates an object with class &lt;code&gt;summary.aov&lt;/code&gt; which is a list and the coefficients table is a matrix. Although &lt;code&gt;anova(lm(...))&lt;/code&gt; creates a data frame that will work with the function without a fatal error, the function &lt;code&gt;anova&lt;/code&gt; has its own way of “pretty” printing [to quote the help file] which is not compatible with the character vector in the P value column and thus will show a P value of 1. So forcing to a data frame is necessary. A minor modification is to ignore the NAs in the Residual row created by the data frame which would otherwise give an error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three decimal places for P values is coded into the function by default and can be changed by the &lt;code&gt;dig&lt;/code&gt; option. For example, &lt;code&gt;dig = 1&lt;/code&gt; will give you &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(&amp;lt;0.1\)&lt;/span&gt;. You can then call your ANOVA table and the &lt;code&gt;fixp&lt;/code&gt; function through &lt;code&gt;knitr::kable()&lt;/code&gt; or your favourite HTML/LaTeX table formatter. e.g. &lt;code&gt;kable(fixp(anova(lm(...))), digits = ...)&lt;/code&gt;. If you don’t want to print NAs, it’s probably better to use the options in your chosen formatting function - e.g. the &lt;code&gt;knitr.kable.NA&lt;/code&gt; option in &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/rmarkdown-cookbook/kable.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;kable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving the valley of intermediate competence</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/using-mapply/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/using-mapply/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/using-mapply/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;if-it-aint-broke-dont-fix-it&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;If it ain’t broke, don’t fix it?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you’ve spent a lot of time learning and practising &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; and you’re pretty comfortable with using functions, if else statements and loops like they teach at introductory programming. What more is there to improve?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the answer is no or you subscribe to the quote above, then turn back now. If yes, continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that even if one has the skills to do fundamental programming competently, there’s always room for improvement or something new to learn. Or you know that there’s a better, more efficient, way to do it but something is holding you back. For me, it’s usually the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a milestone of using &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; I think I have wrapped my head around replacing for loops with the &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; family, specifically &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt;. The last hurdle in delving into functional programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve used iterative coding quite a bit over the years and I’ve been using for loops to do so. As I’ve gotten more competent with applying basic concepts (like loops and functions), I’ve been moving towards optimising my code with more advanced &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; methods. I started with using more manual functions and sourcing functions from external scripts but I was still relying on loops to apply those functions iteratively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know loops are inefficient. I’ve waited &lt;em&gt;days&lt;/em&gt; for computationally intensive loops on large datasets to finish. I know that &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; and co. can be more computationally efficient but in your typical learning something new way, they hadn’t really clicked for me…until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been trying to use &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; family functions where appropriate for years but I’ve never felt comfortable with using them to use them from the start. So, I default back to loops to save time and frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the slow uptake is because the syntax is different to the logic of loops that are taught, even if &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt;’s logic is better from a computing perspective. The syntax and the logic is also inconsistent within the &lt;code&gt;apply&lt;/code&gt; family; a known disadvantage over similar functions (like &lt;code&gt;purrr::map&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let’s focus on a specific case before this becomes a cooking blog: replacing for loops. I’m going to assume that you are competent with manual functions, for loops and lists, and that you want to improve your code. I’m going to focus on lists because they are an efficient way of storing lots of similarly structured data in &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are two ways to replace a for loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;an-example-loop&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;An example loop&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s create an example scenario and data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# some data to use
loop_data &amp;lt;- data.frame(col1 = c(11:15), col2 = c(20:24))

# define variable to change
a &amp;lt;- seq(0.2, 1, 0.2)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; is a data frame with two numeric columns (&lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;code&gt;col2&lt;/code&gt;). We technically won’t use &lt;code&gt;loop_data$col2&lt;/code&gt; but it’s there to create a 5x2 data frame.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; is a variable that we need for our function. There are 5 values.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to add each element of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;loop_data$col1&lt;/code&gt; and save that in a new column &lt;code&gt;loop_data$col1a&lt;/code&gt;. We will also add &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a column in &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; just so we can keep track of which value was used to calculate &lt;code&gt;col1a&lt;/code&gt;. So the final output should have 25 rows (5 observations in &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt; x 5 values of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;) and 4 columns (&lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;col2&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;col1a&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be storing our data in lists in all our scenarios. Note that I create the list to hold the answers (&lt;code&gt;loop_ans&lt;/code&gt;) before the function rather than to append newly calculated answers sequentially to the list within the function. I use the same &lt;code&gt;replicate&lt;/code&gt; function before all the examples. You could also start with an empty list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# data sets stored as a list - must not simplify or it will reduce to a matrix!
loop_ans &amp;lt;- replicate(length(a), loop_data, simplify = FALSE)

# A function to add a value a to a data frame x
loop_function &amp;lt;- function(x, a) {
  x$col1a &amp;lt;- x$col1 + a # add answer to a new column 
  x$a &amp;lt;- a # add a to a new column
  return(x) # give us the updated data frame
}

# Let&amp;#39;s loop
for(i in seq_along(a)){
  loop_ans[[i]] &amp;lt;- loop_function(loop_ans[[i]], a = a[i]) 
}

# merge to single data frame
loop_ans &amp;lt;- do.call(rbind, loop_ans)

# view the data
summary(loop_ans)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##       col1         col2        col1a            a      
##  Min.   :11   Min.   :20   Min.   :11.2   Min.   :0.2  
##  1st Qu.:12   1st Qu.:21   1st Qu.:12.4   1st Qu.:0.4  
##  Median :13   Median :22   Median :13.6   Median :0.6  
##  Mean   :13   Mean   :22   Mean   :13.6   Mean   :0.6  
##  3rd Qu.:14   3rd Qu.:23   3rd Qu.:14.8   3rd Qu.:0.8  
##  Max.   :15   Max.   :24   Max.   :16.0   Max.   :1.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the loop - should be familiar to you. Merging into a single data frame is optional if you want to keep using lists. Now let’s look at &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; for a less elegant solution (!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;lapply&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1. &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; takes a list as input, does stuff and gives a list as output. Hence, the l in &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; stands for list. The difference with loops and &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; is that &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; can only take one input - your data frame (or element in list). This means that we need to add the corresponding value of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; as a column in each element of &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt; - in other words to do part of what &lt;code&gt;loop_function&lt;/code&gt; did but outside the loop/&lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt;. Thus, each data frame in the input list should have three columns: &lt;code&gt;col1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;col2&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, we can add the corresponding &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; value as a column using &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cbind&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# the function only accepts one element: x
lapply_function &amp;lt;- function(x){
  x$col1a &amp;lt;- x$col1 + x$a
  return(x)
}

# Prepare the answer list
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- replicate(length(a), loop_data, simplify = FALSE)

# add a column using mapply
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- mapply(FUN = cbind, lapply_ans, &amp;quot;a&amp;quot; = a, SIMPLIFY = FALSE)

# apply function
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- lapply(lapply_ans, FUN = lapply_function)

# merge to single data frame
lapply_ans &amp;lt;- do.call(rbind, lapply_ans)

# view the data
summary(lapply_ans)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##       col1         col2          a           col1a     
##  Min.   :11   Min.   :20   Min.   :0.2   Min.   :11.2  
##  1st Qu.:12   1st Qu.:21   1st Qu.:0.4   1st Qu.:12.4  
##  Median :13   Median :22   Median :0.6   Median :13.6  
##  Mean   :13   Mean   :22   Mean   :0.6   Mean   :13.6  
##  3rd Qu.:14   3rd Qu.:23   3rd Qu.:0.8   3rd Qu.:14.8  
##  Max.   :15   Max.   :24   Max.   :1.0   Max.   :16.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you see it’s not as simple as the loop or &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; and requires &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; anyway 🤷&lt;br /&gt;
So we can do better…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mapply&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The m in &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; stands for multiple because it takes multiple arguments and applies them to the data. There are some key differences in the structure of the data and the function compared to &lt;code&gt;lapply&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can use the original loop function with two variables!
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The additional variables (&lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; in this example) are written after the function &lt;code&gt;FUN&lt;/code&gt; is defined in &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can also use the original list (&lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt;) without further modification!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to tell &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; not to simplify the output into a matrix by default. Note the use of upper case in &lt;code&gt;SIMPLIFY&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Prepare the answer list
mapply_ans &amp;lt;- replicate(length(a), loop_data, simplify = FALSE)
# mapply function
mapply_ans &amp;lt;- mapply(mapply_ans, FUN = loop_function, a = a, SIMPLIFY = FALSE)
# merge to single data frame
mapply_ans &amp;lt;- do.call(rbind, mapply_ans)
# view the data
summary(mapply_ans)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##       col1         col2        col1a            a      
##  Min.   :11   Min.   :20   Min.   :11.2   Min.   :0.2  
##  1st Qu.:12   1st Qu.:21   1st Qu.:12.4   1st Qu.:0.4  
##  Median :13   Median :22   Median :13.6   Median :0.6  
##  Mean   :13   Mean   :22   Mean   :13.6   Mean   :0.6  
##  3rd Qu.:14   3rd Qu.:23   3rd Qu.:14.8   3rd Qu.:0.8  
##  Max.   :15   Max.   :24   Max.   :16.0   Max.   :1.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; is doing is using the n&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; element of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; with the corresponding n&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; element in the list &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt;. So the fifth value of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; (1.0) is used in the calculations on the 5th data frame in &lt;code&gt;loop_data&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve replace the for loop with a &lt;code&gt;mapply&lt;/code&gt; function! 👏&lt;br /&gt;
Here’s to functional programming. Next up is &lt;code&gt;purrr::map&lt;/code&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick guide to R/exams</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/teaching/rexams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/teaching/rexams/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/teaching/rexams/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-exams.org&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;R/exams&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an R package that generates a reproducible workflow for designing, producing and marking exams.&lt;br /&gt;
Here, I provide a short walkthough for generating an online test for Blackboard - see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.r-exams.org/tutorials/exams2blackboard/&#34;&gt;R/exams website&lt;/a&gt; for some tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;installation&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install R/exams via CRAN with &lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#34;exams&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;running-the-package-for-the-first-time&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Running the package for the first time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;exams&lt;/code&gt; uses &lt;code&gt;rtools&lt;/code&gt; to create zip files. Make sure the proper &lt;code&gt;rtools&lt;/code&gt; is installed. An error message will appear if &lt;code&gt;rtools&lt;/code&gt; does not have permission to create zip files.&lt;br /&gt;
To give permission for creating .zip for windows:
Control Panel &amp;gt; System and Security &amp;gt; System &amp;gt; Advanced System Settings &amp;gt; Environmental Variables &amp;gt; add “C:/RTools/bin”&lt;br /&gt;
You may also need to install dependent packages like &lt;code&gt;tth&lt;/code&gt; for math notation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;types-of-questions&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Types of questions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Single correct answer MCQ (schoice)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multiple correct answer MCQ (mchoice)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numeric answer (num)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;String (string)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloze is another option but is not supported by blackboard, this permits a combination of the above for the MCQ answer list&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;building-an-exam-question&#34; class=&#34;section level1 tabset&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Building an exam question&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several file types that are supported when writing your question but I have stuck with ‘.Rmd’. There are four parts of a question file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The answer list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The solution list for giving feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The meta-information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these sections are defined by a header tag marked by =====. # does not work as a tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;question&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tag for defining the question is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Question&lt;br /&gt;
========&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The various random number generators in R will be your friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sample() # pick n random number(s) from a vector of discrete numbers
runif() # generate a vector of continuous numbers, can set min and max
rnorm() # generate a vector of continuous numbers from a normal distribution with a defined mean and standard deviation&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;things-to-note&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Things to note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code chunk options are in effect. By default figures will have captions, turn it of with &lt;code&gt;fig.caption = &#34;&#34;&lt;/code&gt;. Other useful figure options are figure sizes. Figure options can also be defined when compiling the exam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can show code with &lt;code&gt;echo  = TRUE&lt;/code&gt;, turn off R formatting with &lt;code&gt;results = &#34;asis&#34;&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; hide results with &lt;code&gt;results = &#34;hide&#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LaTeX formatting is fine in markdown and outside code chunks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To allow for randomised questions within a question file I had to escape the R code chunk to render the output as html, else the randomised question would be rendered as R output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can generate a file to go with the question using any R write to file function. Include the file in the question as normal for Rmarkdown - [filename](filelink). Leave this as default or &lt;code&gt;exams&lt;/code&gt; will not be able to find the file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-answer-list&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The answer list&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer subheading is defined by the tag:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer&lt;br /&gt;
========&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bulleted markdown after this tag will be considered the options for an MCQ answer list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;things-to-note-1&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Things to note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;exams&lt;/code&gt; contains several helper functions to make it easy to generate lists of answers.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;answerlist&lt;/code&gt; accepts a vector of answers. It also generates the answer subheading so there is no need to type it in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommend using html in case LaTeX does not render properly, particularly when called as a string in an R code chunk.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not randomise the answer list here, use the metadata, else an incorrect answer will be assigned to be the correct one.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;comment = NA&lt;/code&gt; in the code chunk options will remove the # from the R output.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are also helper functions for various things. &lt;code&gt;mchoice2string()&lt;/code&gt; turns the solutions vector above into binary responses for the meta-information section. &lt;code&gt;num_to_choice&lt;/code&gt; generates a MCQ list of numbers for a numeric answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;solution&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can provide feedback via the solution header, including which answers are correct&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution&lt;br /&gt;
========&lt;br /&gt;
Your solution here or correct answer: &lt;code&gt;code for answer&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;answer[]&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
Answerlist&lt;br /&gt;
-———&lt;br /&gt;
* True&lt;br /&gt;
* False&lt;br /&gt;
* etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important&lt;/strong&gt; There should be no spaces after the header tag title, i.e. markdown formatting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;question-metainformation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Question metainformation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an important section of the question because it defines the correct answer. Metainformation is defined by the tag:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta-information&lt;br /&gt;
================&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Useful variables are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exname = title of question, becomes name of the pool in blackboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extype = type of question (num/schoice/mchoice)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exsolution: order of correct answers in binary (e.g. 01010) for MCQ or R code for numeric output - e.g. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extol = the tolerance range for numeric questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exshuffle = Whether to shuffle the answers or not. This can be used to randomly select a subset of answers from an answer list. Provide a number of answers for non-numeric questions (e.g. 4 for 4 answers). &lt;code&gt;TRUE/FALSE&lt;/code&gt; is also accepted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;an-example-question&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;An example question&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example displays the correct answer and 3 randomly chosen option out of 6 possible answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Question
========
What is your name?

\```{r question, results = &amp;quot;hide&amp;quot;, echo=F}
# list of possible answer as a character vector
knights_of_camelot &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;Arthur, King of the Britons&amp;quot;, 
                        &amp;quot;Sir Lancelot the Brave&amp;quot;,
                        &amp;quot;Sir Robin the Not-Quite-So-Brave-as-Sir-Lancelot&amp;quot;,
                        &amp;quot;Sir Galahad the Pure&amp;quot;,
                        &amp;quot;Sir Bedevere the Wise&amp;quot;,
                        &amp;quot;Patsy&amp;quot;)

# solution to the vector above                        
solutions &amp;lt;- c(FALSE, TRUE, FALSE, FALSE, FALSE, FALSE)

# explanations (feedback for students)
explanations &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;I didn&amp;#39;t vote for him&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;His favourite colour is blue&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;He doesn&amp;#39;t know the capital of Assyria&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;His favourite colour is blue. No, yel...&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;Knows nothing about swallows&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;Clip Clop&amp;quot;)
\```
        
\```{r answerlist, echo=F, results = &amp;quot;asis&amp;quot;}
# helper function to format the list of possible answers
answerlist(knights_of_camelot, markup = &amp;quot;markdown&amp;quot;)
\```


Solution
========
\```{r solutionlist, echo = FALSE, results = &amp;quot;asis&amp;quot;}
answerlist(ifelse(solultions, &amp;quot;True&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;False&amp;quot;), explanations, markup = &amp;quot;markdown&amp;quot;)
\```

Meta-information
================
exname: Bridgekeeper
extype: schoice
exsolution: `\r mchoice2string(solutions)`
exshuffle: 4
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This renders like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Exam 1

    Question

    What is your name?

        Sir Bedevere the Wise
        Arthur, King of the Britons
        Sir Galahad the Pure
        Sir Lancelot the Brave

    Solution
        False. Knows nothing about swallows
        False. I didn&amp;#39;t vote for him
        False. His favourite colour is blue. No, yel.
        True. His favourite colour is blue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could also skip the solutions vector and include it in the explanations vector like &lt;code&gt;c(&#34;False. I didn&#39;t vote for him&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;. Of course, the solution does not appear immediately in blackboard but make sure the option for solutions and feedback to appear is checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;compiling-the-exam&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Compiling the exam&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have written a script to compile the exam.
The compiling function (&lt;code&gt;exams2blackboard&lt;/code&gt;) requires a &lt;em&gt;list&lt;/em&gt; of file names to generate the exam. Each file represents a question. Versions of a question (&lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;) generate a pool of questions. The list should not contain subdirectories or files not to be included in the exam. &lt;code&gt;exams2html&lt;/code&gt; is a means of checking a file/list of exam questions renders properly in html (or &lt;code&gt;exams2pdf&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several means of customising the metadata of the exam. Here I have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turned off partial marks - is TRUE by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;used custom directories to search for the questions and save the output zip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set 10 copies for each question using the variable &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set the name of the zip file using the variable &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set the number of points for each question to 1, default = 10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(&amp;quot;exams&amp;quot;)
options(device.ask.default = FALSE)

## content and output directory
mydir &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;C:/Users/kongj/OneDrive - TCDUD.onmicrosoft.com/Teaching/Biostats/Midsem MCQ&amp;quot;

## define exam questions (each item in list is a pool)
myexam &amp;lt;- list.files(paste0(mydir,&amp;quot;/questions&amp;quot;), pattern = &amp;quot;.Rmd&amp;quot;)

# render single question
#exams2html(list(&amp;quot;question3.Rmd&amp;quot;), edir = paste0(mydir,&amp;quot;/questions&amp;quot;))

## generate .zip with Blackboard exam with n replicates
exams2blackboard(file = myexam, n = 10, name = &amp;#39;Jacinta&amp;#39;, dir = mydir,
                 edir = paste0(mydir,&amp;quot;/questions&amp;quot;),
                 eval = list(partial = FALSE, negative = FALSE),
                 points = 1
                 )

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;things-to-note-2&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Things to note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can create a mix of questions in the exam by defining it in the list of questions but it is not recommended for generating pools of questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the exam is complied with no partial marks, then the blackboard exam will have no partial marks even if the option is checked within blackboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can generate a pool of questions by compiling a single question and uploading that zip file to Blackboard under “Import Pool”. This is useful for creating random block tests in Blackboard if the compiled zip file is not suitable as an test right away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transparent graphing for dark backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-02-01-transparent-graphing-for-dark-backgrounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-02-01-transparent-graphing-for-dark-backgrounds/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2021-02-01-transparent-graphing-for-dark-backgrounds/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m not usually a dark background person but I’m open to the dark side. I wanted to make a solid coloured graph with a transparent background that would show up nicely but &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; doesn’t have a set theme for that. A clean solid fill and transparency requires some specific customisation so here is a reproducible example for you using the built-in &lt;code&gt;trees&lt;/code&gt; dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;tree_graph &amp;lt;- ggplot(data = trees, 
       mapping = aes(x = Height, 
                     y = Girth)) + 
    geom_point(size = 0.5, colour = &amp;quot;#B8DE29FF&amp;quot;) + 
    geom_smooth(method = &amp;quot;lm&amp;quot;, se = FALSE, col = &amp;quot;#B8DE29FF&amp;quot;) + 
    geom_abline(intercept = 0, slope = 1, col = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, lwd = 0.5, lty = 2) + 
    theme_classic() +
    theme(plot.background = element_rect(fill = &amp;quot;transparent&amp;quot;, color = NA),
          panel.background = element_rect(fill = &amp;quot;transparent&amp;quot;),
          axis.text = element_text(colour = &amp;quot;#B8DE29FF&amp;quot;, size = 8),
          axis.title = element_text(colour = &amp;quot;#B8DE29FF&amp;quot;, size = 8),
          axis.line = element_line(colour = &amp;quot;#B8DE29FF&amp;quot;),
          axis.ticks = element_line(colour = &amp;quot;#B8DE29FF&amp;quot;))

ggsave(tree_graph, filename = &amp;quot;tree_graph.png&amp;quot;, bg = &amp;quot;transparent&amp;quot;, type = &amp;quot;cairo&amp;quot;, width = 10, height = 10, dpi = 300)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of generally useful elements added on purpose:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;geom_smooth&lt;/code&gt; creates an automatically fitted linear model (defined using &lt;code&gt;method = &#34;lm&#34;&lt;/code&gt;). I have turned off plotting the standard errors (on by default) and manually set the colour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;geom_abline&lt;/code&gt; is your standard straight line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;theme&lt;/code&gt; is where the customisation begins:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;plot.background&lt;/code&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;code&gt;panel.background&lt;/code&gt; are set to transparent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The various axis elements are set to the fill colour (a nice &lt;code&gt;viridis&lt;/code&gt; green) and desired text size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggsave&lt;/code&gt; specifies that the background is transparent and to save it using the Cairo engine (&lt;code&gt;type = &#34;cairo&#34;&lt;/code&gt;). Cairo will create a vector based image so resizing the png isn’t an issue since the small font size is already defined.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can also use &lt;code&gt;cairo-png&lt;/code&gt; but the graph height and width options appear to be ignored.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don’t save it as a Cairo png, then the text will still have a white outline and won’t be a clean solid fill&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biostatistics tutorials</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/project/biostats-tutorials/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/project/biostats-tutorials/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/project/biostats-tutorials/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;biostats.tutorials&lt;/code&gt; is an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; package of &lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; tutorials for introductory biostatistics and &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;set-up&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Set up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to set up our computer to start using tutorials in R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow this checklist in order to make sure you are set up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed R version 4.0 or above? - if not, install/update R
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can check your R package version using &lt;code&gt;R.version()$version.string&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed RStudio version 1.0.136 or above? - if not install/update RStudio
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can check your RStudio version using &lt;code&gt;RStudio.Version()$version&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you installed the following packages? - if not use &lt;code&gt;install.packages()&lt;/code&gt; to do so
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;learnr&lt;/code&gt; - needed to run the tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;remotes&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;devtools&lt;/code&gt;) - needed to install the tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;knitr&lt;/code&gt; - for displaying content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If everything works then you should see a Tutorials tab in one of your RStudio windows (perhaps next to Environment and History)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;installing-the-tutorials&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installing the tutorials&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we need to install the tutorial. The tutorials are stored in a Package available on GitHub. You will only have to install the package once at the beginning.&lt;br /&gt;
Use the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;jacintak/biostats&amp;quot;, dependencies = TRUE)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are asked to install any other packages, choose yes but don’t do any compiling (press no if asked).&lt;br /&gt;
If the package installed properly, you should automatically see the tutorials in the Tutorial tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;running-a-tutorial&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Running a tutorial&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be able to run a tutorial from the Tutorial tab when you open RStudio without needing to do anything.&lt;br /&gt;
Make sure it’s a tutorial from the &lt;code&gt;biostats.tutorials&lt;/code&gt; package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you click run tutorial, the tutorial will show up in the tab. You can click the “Show in new window” icon to open it in another window. Press the “Home” icon to return to the Tutorials tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that doesn’t work use this code and the tutorial will open in another window:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;learnr::run_tutorial(&amp;quot;&amp;lt;insert name of the tutorial to run&amp;gt;&amp;quot;, package = &amp;quot;biostats.tutorials&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If neither works, check that the &lt;code&gt;biostats.tutorials&lt;/code&gt; package installed properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quit a tutorial by pressing the “Stop” icon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
