<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jason K. Axford | Jacinta&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>/authors/jason-k.-axford/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/jason-k.-axford/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Jason K. Axford</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Jason K. Axford</title>
      <link>/authors/jason-k.-axford/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linking thermal adaptation and life-history theory explains latitudinal patterns of voltinism</title>
      <link>/publication/2019-ptrsb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2019-ptrsb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insect life cycles are adapted to a seasonal climate by expressing alternative voltinism phenotypes—the number of generations in a year. Variation in voltinism phenotypes along latitudinal gradients may be generated by developmental traits at critical life stages, such as eggs. Both voltinism and egg development are thermally determined traits, yet independently derived models of voltinism and thermal adaptation refer to the evolution of dormancy and thermal sensitivity of development rate, respectively, as independent influences on life history. To reconcile these models and test their respective predictions, we characterized patterns of voltinism and thermal response of egg development rate along a latitudinal temperature gradient using the matchstick grasshopper genus &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt;. We found remarkably strong variation in voltinism patterns, as well as corresponding egg dormancy patterns and thermal responses of egg development. Our results show that the switch in voltinism along the latitudinal gradient was explained by the combined predictions of the evolution of voltinism and of thermal adaptation. We suggest that latitudinal patterns in thermal responses and corresponding life histories need to consider the evolution of thermal response curves within the context of seasonal temperature cycles rather than based solely on optimality and trade-offs in performance. This article is part of the theme issue ‘Physiological diversity, biodiversity patterns and global climate change: testing key hypotheses involving temperature and oxygen’.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel applications of thermocyclers for phenotyping invertebrate thermal responses</title>
      <link>/publication/2016-mee/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/2016-mee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-throughput genomic methods are increasingly used to investigate invertebrate thermal responses with greater dimensionality and resolution than previously achieved. However, corresponding methods for characterizing invertebrate phenotypes are still lacking. To scale up the characterization of invertebrate thermal responses, we propose a novel use of thermocyclers as temperature-controlled incubators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we tested the performance of thermocyclers as incubators and demonstrated the application of this method to efficiently characterize the thermal responses of model and non-model invertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found the thermocyclers performed with high precision, accuracy and resolution under various and fluctuating ambient conditions. We were able to successfully characterize the temperature-dependent development of grasshopper eggs (&lt;em&gt;Warramaba virgo&lt;/em&gt;), as well as the effects of fluctuating temperature cycles on the survival of mosquito eggs (&lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/em&gt;) and developmental success of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila simulans&lt;/em&gt; larvae, all with similar survival rates to conventional methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thermocyclers are a general and transferrable means to scale up current methods of incubating small invertebrates. They permit rapid characterization of high-dimensional physiological responses to natural thermal regimes. When combined with existing approaches in thermal and evolutionary biology, these methods will advance our understanding of, and ability to predict, biological adaptations and responses to environmental changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
