<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks | Jacinta&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jacintak.github.io/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jacintak.github.io/img/icon-512.png</url>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ICE 2024</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/ICE2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/ICE2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;symposium-description&#34;&gt;Symposium description&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am organising a symposium on using physiology in insect mass-rearing practice at the International Congress of Entomology in Kyoto, Japan in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rearing insects en masse is crucial for numerous industries. Mass reared insects are used for releases related to pollination, disease control, conservation or pest management, and for food and feed production and waste processing. Physiological performance underpins the quantities and qualities of insects necessary for success in mass rearing programs. In turn, performance gains and deficits depend on biotic and abiotic factors like diet, temperature, social environments, and disease (e.g. viruses). We will connect experts working on various modulators of performance across as many applications as possible and showcase how insect physiology can be leveraged to optimise mass rearing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BES 2022</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BES2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BES2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thermal tolerances, such as critical temperatures, are important indices for understanding an organism’s vulnerability to changing environmental temperature. Differences in thermal tolerance over ontogeny may generate a ‘thermal bottleneck’ that sets the climate vulnerability for organisms with complex life cycles. However, a species’ microhabitat preference and methodological differences among studies can generate confounding variation in thermal tolerance that may mask trends in large-scale comparative studies and may hinder our ability to assess climate change vulnerability within and among species. Here, we evaluated two approaches to resolving ontogenetic and environmental drivers of thermal tolerance and methodological variation: mathematical standardisation of thermal tolerance and classifying microhabitat preferences. Using phylogenetically informed, multi-level models with a global dataset of upper critical temperatures from 438 Anuran species, we found ontogenetic trends in thermal tolerance were similar across microhabitat preferences and standardising critical temperatures against common methodological variation had little impact on our conclusions. Our results suggested thermal bottlenecks are not strongly present in Anurans but instead, implied strong developmental or genetic conservatism of thermal tolerance within families and ecotypes. We discussed considerations for resolving confounding variation to interpret thermal tolerance at a macrophysiological scale.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Society for Experimental Biology Annual Meeting</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/SEB2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 14:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/SEB2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Insect life cycles are adapted to a seasonal climate by expressing alternative voltinism phenotypes—the number of generations in a year. The problem is to understand how this phenotypic variation along latitudinal gradients is generated through the interactions between environmental factors, like temperature, and the traits of organisms, like development rate and dormancy. However, our current understanding is limited by how thermal responses are characterised, competing theories of thermal adaptation and an incomplete understanding of complex life cycles. Using the widely distributed grasshopper genus &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt; as a model, we aimed to reconcile theories of thermal adaptation and tested their respective predictions. We hypothesised that the egg stage was a critical life stage for generating latitudinal patterns of voltinism in &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt;. We described patterns of voltinism and thermal response of egg development rate within and among species of &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt; along a latitudinal temperature gradient. We found a latitudinal pattern of univoltinism at high latitudes and multivoltinism at low latitudes that corresponded with remarkably strong divergence in egg dormancy patterns and thermal responses of egg development. We argue that the switch in voltinism along the latitudinal gradient was generated by the combined predictions of the evolution of voltinism and of thermal adaptation. We conclude that analyses of latitudinal patterns in thermal responses and corresponding life histories need to consider the evolution of thermal response curves within the context of seasonal temperature cycles rather than based solely on optimality and trade-offs in performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BES Macro 2021</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BESMacro2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BESMacro2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IEA2021</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/IEA2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/IEA2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
