<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 | Jacinta&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication_types/2/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jacintak.github.io/publication_types/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jacintak.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication_types/2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linking thermal adaptation and life-history theory explains latitudinal patterns of voltinism</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2019-PTRSB/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2019-PTRSB/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insect life cycles are adapted to a seasonal climate by expressing alternative voltinism phenotypes—the number of generations in a year. Variation in voltinism phenotypes along latitudinal gradients may be generated by developmental traits at critical life stages, such as eggs. Both voltinism and egg development are thermally determined traits, yet independently derived models of voltinism and thermal adaptation refer to the evolution of dormancy and thermal sensitivity of development rate, respectively, as independent influences on life history. To reconcile these models and test their respective predictions, we characterized patterns of voltinism and thermal response of egg development rate along a latitudinal temperature gradient using the matchstick grasshopper genus &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt;. We found remarkably strong variation in voltinism patterns, as well as corresponding egg dormancy patterns and thermal responses of egg development. Our results show that the switch in voltinism along the latitudinal gradient was explained by the combined predictions of the evolution of voltinism and of thermal adaptation. We suggest that latitudinal patterns in thermal responses and corresponding life histories need to consider the evolution of thermal response curves within the context of seasonal temperature cycles rather than based solely on optimality and trade-offs in performance. This article is part of the theme issue ‘Physiological diversity, biodiversity patterns and global climate change: testing key hypotheses involving temperature and oxygen’.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Summer egg diapause in a matchstick grasshopper synchronises the life cycle and buffers thermal extremes</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2018-inte-zool/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2018-inte-zool/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phenological response is among the most important traits affecting a species&#39; sensitivity to climate. In insects, strongly seasonal environments often select for a univoltine life-cycle such that one seasonal extreme is avoided as an inactive stage. Through understanding the underlying mechanisms for univoltinism, and the consequences of its failure, we can better predict insect responses to climate change. Here we combine empirical data and simulation studies to investigate the consequences of an unusual diapause mechanism in a parthenogenetic matchstick grasshopper, &lt;em&gt;Warramaba virgo&lt;/em&gt;, from arid southern Australia. Our field body temperature measurements indicate that this species is a thermoconformer and our laboratory studies of the thermal response of feeding rate imply strong constraints on winter activity. However, the species exhibits no obligate winter diapause, and eggs can develop in one month under constant temperatures approximating the mean soil temperature at the time of oviposition (summer). We show that diurnal temperature cycles exceeding a peak of 36 degrees C inhibit egg development in summer, and that this is sufficient to prevent autumnal hatching of eggs. Development is also strongly retarded below 24 degrees C. Microclimate-driven simulation studies of egg development show that these thermal responses provide robust maintenance of a univoltine life cycle, thereby resulting in survival of heat stress as an egg (due to limited developmental state) and avoidance of cold stress as a nymph and adult (due to overwintering in the soil as an egg). This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanistic models for predicting insect responses to climate change</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2016-COIS/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2016-COIS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mechanistic models of the impacts of climate change on insects can be seen as very specific hypotheses about the connections between microclimate, ecophysiology and vital rates. These models must adequately capture stage-specific responses, carry-over effects between successive stages, and the evolutionary potential of the functional traits involved in complex insect life-cycles. Here we highlight key considerations for current approaches to mechanistic modelling of insect responses to climate change. We illustrate these considerations within a general mechanistic framework incorporating the thermodynamic linkages between microclimate and heat, water and nutrient exchange throughout the life-cycle under different climate scenarios. We emphasise how such a holistic perspective will provide increasingly robust insights into how insects adapt and respond to changing climates.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel applications of thermocyclers for phenotyping invertebrate thermal responses</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2016-MEE/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2016-MEE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-throughput genomic methods are increasingly used to investigate invertebrate thermal responses with greater dimensionality and resolution than previously achieved. However, corresponding methods for characterizing invertebrate phenotypes are still lacking. To scale up the characterization of invertebrate thermal responses, we propose a novel use of thermocyclers as temperature-controlled incubators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we tested the performance of thermocyclers as incubators and demonstrated the application of this method to efficiently characterize the thermal responses of model and non-model invertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found the thermocyclers performed with high precision, accuracy and resolution under various and fluctuating ambient conditions. We were able to successfully characterize the temperature-dependent development of grasshopper eggs (&lt;em&gt;Warramaba virgo&lt;/em&gt;), as well as the effects of fluctuating temperature cycles on the survival of mosquito eggs (&lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/em&gt;) and developmental success of &lt;em&gt;Drosophila simulans&lt;/em&gt; larvae, all with similar survival rates to conventional methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thermocyclers are a general and transferrable means to scale up current methods of incubating small invertebrates. They permit rapid characterization of high-dimensional physiological responses to natural thermal regimes. When combined with existing approaches in thermal and evolutionary biology, these methods will advance our understanding of, and ability to predict, biological adaptations and responses to environmental changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
