<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PhD | Jacinta&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>https://jacintak.github.io/tags/PhD/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jacintak.github.io/tags/PhD/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>PhD</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jacintak.github.io/img/icon-512.png</url>
      <title>PhD</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/tags/PhD/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parthenogenesis without costs in a grasshopper with hybrid origins</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2022-Science/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2022-Science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rarity of parthenogenetic species is typically attributed to the reduced genetic variability that accompanies the absence of sex, yet natural parthenogens can be surprisingly successful. Ecological success is often proposed to derive from hybridization through enhanced genetic diversity from repetitive origins or enhanced phenotypic breadth from heterosis. Here, we tested and rejected both hypotheses in a classic parthenogen, the diploid grasshopper Warramaba virgo. Genetic data revealed a single hybrid mating origin at least 0.25 million years ago, and comparative analyses of 14 physiological and life history traits showed no evidence for altered fitness relative to its sexual progenitors. Our findings imply that the rarity of parthenogenesis is due to constraints on origin rather than to rapid extinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;media-articles&#34;&gt;Media articles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.unimelb.edu.au/newsroom/news/2022/june/males-need-not-apply-research-on-grasshopper-species-unravels-the-benefits-of-giving-up-sex&#34;&gt;University of Melbourne Pursuit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/this-australian-grasshopper-gave-up-sex-250-000-years-ago-and-its-doing-fine-184241&#34;&gt;The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Society for Experimental Biology Annual Meeting</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/SEB2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 14:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/SEB2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Insect life cycles are adapted to a seasonal climate by expressing alternative voltinism phenotypes—the number of generations in a year. The problem is to understand how this phenotypic variation along latitudinal gradients is generated through the interactions between environmental factors, like temperature, and the traits of organisms, like development rate and dormancy. However, our current understanding is limited by how thermal responses are characterised, competing theories of thermal adaptation and an incomplete understanding of complex life cycles. Using the widely distributed grasshopper genus &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt; as a model, we aimed to reconcile theories of thermal adaptation and tested their respective predictions. We hypothesised that the egg stage was a critical life stage for generating latitudinal patterns of voltinism in &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt;. We described patterns of voltinism and thermal response of egg development rate within and among species of &lt;em&gt;Warramaba&lt;/em&gt; along a latitudinal temperature gradient. We found a latitudinal pattern of univoltinism at high latitudes and multivoltinism at low latitudes that corresponded with remarkably strong divergence in egg dormancy patterns and thermal responses of egg development. We argue that the switch in voltinism along the latitudinal gradient was generated by the combined predictions of the evolution of voltinism and of thermal adaptation. We conclude that analyses of latitudinal patterns in thermal responses and corresponding life histories need to consider the evolution of thermal response curves within the context of seasonal temperature cycles rather than based solely on optimality and trade-offs in performance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jacinta @ Humans of BioSciences</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2020-12-17-jacinta-humans-of-biosciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2020-12-17-jacinta-humans-of-biosciences/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2020-12-17-jacinta-humans-of-biosciences/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was recently featured on Humans of BioSciences, a series about the people of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://biosciences.unimelb.edu.au/&#34;&gt;School of Biosciences&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Melbourne (my alma mater).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the Twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BioSci_UniMelb/status/1339375265961582592&#34;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; and the full interview &lt;a href=&#34;https://biosciences.unimelb.edu.au/news/hbos/jacinta-kong-humans-of-biosciences&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
