<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>postdoc | Jacinta&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>https://jacintak.github.io/tags/postdoc/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jacintak.github.io/tags/postdoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>postdoc</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 17:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jacintak.github.io/img/icon-512.png</url>
      <title>postdoc</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/tags/postdoc/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>BES 2022</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BES2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BES2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thermal tolerances, such as critical temperatures, are important indices for understanding an organism’s vulnerability to changing environmental temperature. Differences in thermal tolerance over ontogeny may generate a ‘thermal bottleneck’ that sets the climate vulnerability for organisms with complex life cycles. However, a species’ microhabitat preference and methodological differences among studies can generate confounding variation in thermal tolerance that may mask trends in large-scale comparative studies and may hinder our ability to assess climate change vulnerability within and among species. Here, we evaluated two approaches to resolving ontogenetic and environmental drivers of thermal tolerance and methodological variation: mathematical standardisation of thermal tolerance and classifying microhabitat preferences. Using phylogenetically informed, multi-level models with a global dataset of upper critical temperatures from 438 Anuran species, we found ontogenetic trends in thermal tolerance were similar across microhabitat preferences and standardising critical temperatures against common methodological variation had little impact on our conclusions. Our results suggested thermal bottlenecks are not strongly present in Anurans but instead, implied strong developmental or genetic conservatism of thermal tolerance within families and ecotypes. We discussed considerations for resolving confounding variation to interpret thermal tolerance at a macrophysiological scale.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heating tolerance of ectotherms is explained by temperature’s non-linear influence on biological rates</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2022-biorxiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/publication/2022-biorxiv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capacity of ectotherms to adjust their thermal tolerance limits through evolution or acclimation seems relatively modest and highly variable, and we lack satisfying explanations for both findings given a limited understanding of what ultimately determines an organism’s thermal tolerance. Here, we test if the amount of heating an ectotherm tolerates throughout a heating event until organismal failure scales with temperature’s non-linear influence on biological rates. To account for the non-linear influence of temperature on biological rates on heating tolerance, we rescaled the duration of heating events of 316 ectothermic taxa acclimated to different temperatures and describe the biological rate-corrected heating duration. This rescaling reveals that the capacity of an organism to resist a heating event is in fact remarkably constant across any acclimation temperature, enabling high-precision estimates of how organismal thermal tolerance limits vary under different thermal regimes. We also find that faster heating consistently reduces biological rate-corrected heating durations, which helps further explain why thermal tolerance limits seem so variable on absolute temperature scales. Existing paradigms are that heating tolerances and thermal tolerance limits reflect incomplete metabolic compensatory responses, are constrained by evolutionary conservatism, or index failure of systems such as membrane function; our data provide a different perspective and show that an organism’s thermal tolerance emerges from the interaction between the non-linear thermal dependence of biological rates and heating durations, which is an approximately-fixed property of a species.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BES Macro 2021</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BESMacro2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/BESMacro2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IEA2021</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/IEA2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/talk/IEA2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jacinta @ Humans of BioSciences</title>
      <link>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2020-12-17-jacinta-humans-of-biosciences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jacintak.github.io/post/2020-12-17-jacinta-humans-of-biosciences/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://jacintak.github.io/post/2020-12-17-jacinta-humans-of-biosciences/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was recently featured on Humans of BioSciences, a series about the people of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://biosciences.unimelb.edu.au/&#34;&gt;School of Biosciences&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Melbourne (my alma mater).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the Twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/BioSci_UniMelb/status/1339375265961582592&#34;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; and the full interview &lt;a href=&#34;https://biosciences.unimelb.edu.au/news/hbos/jacinta-kong-humans-of-biosciences&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
